<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newnams nightcrowe A bird that breedeth braules in many families and housholdes. Wherein is remembred that kindely and prouident regard which fathers ought to haue towards their sonnes. Together with a diciphring of the iniurious dealinges of some younger sorte of stepdames.</title>
            <author>Newnham, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121837</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856999</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856999</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22657</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08134)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22657)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1147:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newnams nightcrowe A bird that breedeth braules in many families and housholdes. Wherein is remembred that kindely and prouident regard which fathers ought to haue towards their sonnes. Together with a diciphring of the iniurious dealinges of some younger sorte of stepdames.</title>
                  <author>Newnham, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 50, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Priuted [sic] by Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Iohn Newnham.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The nightcrowe.</note>
                  <note>D4v has a paragraph mark at foot. Variant: D4r has a cancel page pasted over original page, which has seven more lines; no paragraph mark on verso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stepmothers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Parent and child --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Newnams Nightcrowe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Bird that breedeth braules in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Families and Houſholdes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is remembred that kindely and prouident regard which Fathers ought to haue towards their Sonnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with a diſciphring of the iniurious dealinges of ſome younger ſorte of ſtepdames.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Vnicuique ſecundum opera cius.</p>
               <bibl>Cor. 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Vix reijcis florem qui dulcem prebet odorem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by Iohn Wolfe. 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:2"/>
            <head>The Bookes purpoſe.</head>
            <l>For widdowes and elder brothers,</l>
            <l>For children that haue loſt their mothers.</l>
            <l>Or be iniured by ſtepdames might.</l>
            <l>And Sonnes that loſt their births right.</l>
            <l>With others needyng reſtitution.</l>
            <l>Theſe finde in me ſome meete fruition.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right worſhipful Maiſter Thomas</hi> Owen Eſquire, one of the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties learned Seriants at the <hi>Lawe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time King Darius in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaded Scithia, the people of the ſame did retire and gyue back ſo much from the force and firſt brunt of the inuador that in a maner they ſeemed to giue ouer and relinquiſhe the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that part, which was of beſt fertility, and were nowe entring into their deſert of their land. Darius ſent to knowe what they meant and how farre they purpoſed to flie, they aunſwered wee haue no Citties to fight for, but as ſoone as Darius ſhall beginne to medle with the Townes, and Monumentes of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and aunceſters, hee ſhall knowe whether the Cittizens can fight. It is nowe more then twenty yeeres ſpace, ſince it hath been my fortune to beare the aſſaultes, dammage, iniury, diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortes, and vnkindneſſe of a ſtepdame, by her o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermuch preuailing, which oftentimes is found to bee as puiſſant in vanquiſhing as the ſtrong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Darius. All this I thought to haue put vp
<pb facs="tcp:22657:3"/>and giuen place vnto by ſilent patience, as a croſſe ordained for mee, vntill at length ſhee proceeded ſo farre in malignity, as I thought it intollerable: and that was by an vtter ſupplanting and diſheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of mee in ſome meane or competent porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, her driftes thus extending to the ſpoiling mee of my birth-right, which to euerie man is the beſt Monument of his parent, I could not but be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with that pricke or inſtinct of Nature, which ſheweth it ſelfe in the leaſte creatures, of which it is ſaide: <hi>Habet muſca ſplenem &amp; formicae ſua bilis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi> The Flie will reſiſt and the Ant will turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Nowe for that ſome purpoſe or ende of knowledge and inſight is to drawe good out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and to make medicines of diſeaſes, I thought it good with ſome labour beſtowed to conuert the harme of my owne calamitie, to the inſtruction of ſome and benefit of others, in no ſmall number. And becauſe the ſubiect of the whole matter, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſhroud it ſelfe moſt vnder the nature, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, and maners of a ſtepdam, which perſwadeth as much by night as by day, ſhee is vulgarly called the Nightcrow, beſt worthy to be my childs God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother and to haue the preheminency of the name. And although all ſorts of fowle <hi>Coruini ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris</hi>) of crowes kinde, were forbidden to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, which argueth ſome ill property, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholeſome, or vnſauorie taſte of the fleſh of that kind, yet I hope there is nothing in this intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or ſpirituall bird, that may offende or diſlike the taſte of any good Chriſtian or true Iſraelite. The
<pb facs="tcp:22657:3"/>Diuines howſoeuer it commeth to paſſe make the Crowe a figure of procraſtination, and deferring to doe good. It may be of his crie or voice, and the continual iterating of this worde, <hi>cra cra,</hi> put to it one letter, it is <hi>cras,</hi> ſo is there nothing in her mouth (if ſhe could ſpeak Engliſh) but to morrow, to morrow. Therefore it pleaſeth ſome of them (when they woulde counſel vs to beware of defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, or the performing of good deeds) to bid vs beware wyth the Iſraelites to eate Crows fleſh: as though Crowes by property or nature be hinderers in al goodneſſe, and no furtherers. They that by the like hap are brought into the aduerſe condition of diſheriſon, be not many, nor yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, the moſt being of ſome honeſt valure, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer affection hath wrought to the verefying of that ſaying, Prou. 13. Some men are rich, though they haue nothing, &amp; ſome men are poore, hauing great riches. This notwithſtanding no man is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally willing to giue place vnto wrong. <hi>Appetere proprium bonum eſt omnibus naturale.</hi> To deſire our owne good is naturall to all men, ſaieth Ariſtotle. And therefore that wiſe Prince and louing Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Lacedemonians: Ageſilaus ſeeing a childe taking a mouſe by the taile, and pretilie to pull him out of his hole, the mouſe turning againe, bit the childe by the fingers, &amp; ſo eſcaped. Which ſmall and childiſh matter, he applied to waightie and ſadde purpoſe: bidding indeede the beſt of his Captaines to take an example hereof, ſaying: If ſo little a beaſt will reſiſt iniurie, what ſhould men of
<pb facs="tcp:22657:4"/>valure do if they be prouoked. God of his infinit goodneſſe giue grace vnto all wrong doers, &amp; ſuch as haue erred in this behalfe, through ill counſel, or other illuſion, to remoue from themſelues, &amp; their way to eternitie, that blocke of iniurious miſdoing, and in the meane time to ſende likewiſe the grace and gift of Chriſtian patience to the iniured of this ſorte till remedie be vouchſafed.</p>
            <p>Thus not with the leaſt of your well willers nor with the laſt of your vndeſeruing accomptance, I wiſh you long life with the accompliſhment of true happines, preſuming to dedicate to your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation and patronage, the homely fruites of this my ruſticke labor.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips dutifully, <hi>&amp; dignitatis tuae cum ſalute ſtudioſus.</hi> Iohn Newnham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough (friendly Reader) I haue read that the Emperour Tiberius, ſo little conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to any purpoſe or motion of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny in himſelfe that hee would openly ſay: <hi>In a free Citie tongues ſhould be free,</hi> yet in the bodie of this ſimple treatiſe, wherein I ſeeme in part to haue ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict with them that be nymble and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at the weapon of tongues, I truſt I haue not ouer-laſhed my ſelfe to the miſuſing or offence of my owne tongue, well I wot that folke ſhall giue an account for idle wordes, but thoſe bee not idle that are meant to admoniſh, exhort, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue, commende, or miſprayſe, ſo long as they bee ſpoken truely and ſoundly. If any wordes of this kinde be more than the infirmitie of any woman or man would willingly heare of, let him wit, that which they diſlike or finde not belonging to themſelues it pertayneth to ſome others as an admonition of the fault. I wot well that beſides Nightcrowes, there be <hi>Noctuae &amp; Veſpertiliones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be alſo <hi>Momi</hi> which be <hi>mimi,</hi> in Engliſh: I meane bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie controullers, and but ſmall dooers themſelues: as light and trueth is delectable to all other birdes and creatures of ſound eye-ſight, ſo vnto theſe, playne truth without ſtarching and ſetting foorth in order is eyther ſo offenſiue or ſeemeth ſo boyſterous in their tender eyes, and they can as ill away with it as that mother in lawe which deſerueth to bee called a Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, can abide to take delight in her husbands firſt chirdren. Neither commeth this woorde Stepdame of the ſpeakers ill ſpeech or terming, but in deede is drawne from the parties ill doing: although perhaps the Grammarians will ſay, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerca</hi> is a compound worde, <hi>quaſi noua furca,</hi> in engliſh, a newe frame of three peeces prepared and ſet vp for ſome pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. By that word God forbid I ſhould meane all mothers in lawes of whome I dare vowe and affirme there bee a great number ſo kindly to their husbandes children, that they may
<pb facs="tcp:22657:5"/>well be called mothers. The abuſe of a fewe ſometime maketh all of that ſute or ſort, to be blamed, <hi>propter paucas inuiſa ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus omnes mulieres</hi> ſayth Terence: for a fewe Stepdames ſake we are all called Stepmothers. To be ſhort, I would conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeech all mother in lawes in generall, to haue this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my meaning that haue aduentured to meddle in this kind of matter, chiefely in fauour of the ouerborne, motherleſſe and of the poore innocents, whoſe Angels be before the throne of God, that as we are ſure one Crowe pulleth not out anothers eyes, ſo I hope this my Nightcrowe ſhall ſpiritually or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally doe good vnto many, euen of them that rightly deſerue that name.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:5"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THat the vertue, thriuing and proſperitie of children are for the moſt part wrought by the fathers good examples and instructions. Chap. <hi>I.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the vice and other infelicitie of children, moſtly proceedeth of the fathers ill examples. Chap. <hi>II.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That fathers ought not to prouoke their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to wrath or diſobedience. Chap. <hi>III.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That fathers ought to deale kindly and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not preiudicially or fraudulently towards their children. Chap. <hi>IIII.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That fathers or parents ought not to diſpoſe their goods or landes after priuate fancie. Chap. V.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond part.</head>
               <item>OF the vngentle dealing of ſome Stepmothers towardes their husbands children. Chap. vj.</item>
               <item>That ſtepmothers ought not to be priuate or falſe accuſers of their husbandes children more than of others. Chap. vij.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22657:6"/>
That Stepmothers ought not to ſupplant or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure diſheriting of their husbandes eldeſt ſonnes. Chap. viij.</item>
               <item>That diſheriting of the eldeſt ſonne without ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great lawfull cauſe is an act verie wrongfull and vngodly Chap. ix.</item>
               <item>That procurers and counſailors of diſheriſon and all wrong doing ought to make or procure reſtitution. Chap. x.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:6"/>
            <head>The firſt part of this treatiſe (ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Night-crowe) perſwadeth in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine kindely points pertaining to a natural father, the regard whereof, may worke a meete pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue or preuention againſt a womans inchanting or peruerting.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. That the vertue, thriuing, and proſperitie of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are for the moſt parte wrought by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good examples and inſtructions.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Olon, that was reputed ſo wiſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident a lawe-maker for the Athenians, being aſked howe a State or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth might beſt be kept vpright, and longeſt endure: mary (ſaith he) if ſubiects obey their Magiſtrates, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates obey the lawes: as if hee woulde ſay, It is not enough if the ſubiects obey, &amp; the Magiſtrates neglect the obſeruing of laws themſelues, but theſe muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey firſt, that the others may learne obedience, otherwiſe they are like to reape ſuch fruits as they ſowe by examples. As ſubiects and inferiors are contained within bounds of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and duety by lawes, ſo princes, paſtors, parents, and all ſuperiours are ſubiected to other lawes, for the moſt parte haue a ſuperior Iudge, whereby is performed the earthlie Hierarchie ſo well pleaſing vnto God, and ſo much deſired of good men, whiles they commaund by their owne lawes, they ſtand obliged by no leſſe duetie of obedience to the law of God, and of nature. And ſpecially Parents, who are ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22657:7"/>déepelie bound to loue and tender their children, that brute beaſts and birds may reproue &amp; controll many. The thing that is moſt requiſite to be found in them, is naturall loue augmented and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the ſame which Chriſt ſo care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully commended to his children, to wit, charitie. Charitie makes one heart of many: it is the way of man vnto God, and the way of god to man: but he that expreſſeth himſelfe in his actions to faile, in the duety of naturall loue, is not worthy to be counted an obſeruer of the bond of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>This Charitie or wonderfull newe loue, Chriſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly left vnto his children by forme of an expreſſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but alſo taught and confirmed the ſame by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of himſelfe, in the vnſpeakable myſterie of Sacraments: folke are taught better by example of doing then by words, and ſuch examples are alwayes to be drawne from the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to the inferiour. They whom nature or order hath preferred in degrée before others, will alwayes bee looked vppon for their examples, which therefore had néede to bée good. For that which is doone by example, the inferiours will thinke they may lawfullie doe the like. Good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples doe edifie and vpholde, ill examples do deſtroy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found. Humanitie is taught by the lawe of Nature. If pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents by their example ſhould teach the contrarie, what do they elſe but indeuour to tranſfourme men into beaſts: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning firſt to perfourme it in their owne children. Theſe will (ſay they) bée Chriſtians, and of the faithfull, and yet Saint Iames ſaieth, <hi>Fides ſine operibus mortua eſt:</hi> Faith without workes is dead. They muſt ſhewe vs bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter examples to come from them towardes their children, then colde friendſhip peruerting of order; and ſowing ſéedes of diſſention in their owne houſe. Good workes generallie tende towardes the clothing of the ſoules nakedneſſe, but good workes in performing the will of GOD in our owne houſe, may prooue a preſeruatiue againſt the plague or poyſon of imputient mindes, or more rather remedy againſt the ruine of Soules, deſcended in our owne oſſpring.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22657:7"/>Pietie or godlines, which is a vertue annexed vnto Iuſtice, beſides the fourth expreſſed Commandement, compelleth children to loue and honour their Parentes, their kindred, and their countrey, but yet Parents muſt not thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vntouched, or vnbound by this commaundement, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by a ſecondarie meanes the ſame willeth and inuiteth Parentes to honour, and eſpeciallie to regarde theyr chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Which honouring or ſpeciall regarding, is to bée perfourmed of eche partie in heart, worde, and déede. As for the loue of people at large, it is to bée accounted as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table as the faire weather, or as permanent as the calmes of the Sea. But the naturall and the kindelie loue of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes towardes their children, is, or ought to bee, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and readie, as we woulde wiſh to finde the lone and fauour of GOD towardes vs. Neyther can they fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe a better example giuer then Chriſt hymſelfe, who hath taught them to commende and bequeath loue vnto theyr Children, for if there had béene anie thing more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, hée woulde haue commended it vnto his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Diſciples before this. Neuer were more néede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the Parentes examples of loue and well dooing, then nowe, ſéeing children finde them ſcarce to be had at the handes of others. <hi>Pondus meum amor meus,</hi> ſaieth Saint Auguſtine, My waight is my loue. And vnto them that lacke waight herein, ſhall that bée ſayde, <hi>Diſcedite a me operarij iniquitatis,</hi> Goe from mée ye workers of iniquitie Luke the thirtéenth. It is no ſuſpected or vnſound coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſet downe in Decretals by theſe wordes, <hi>Ante omnia opus eſt vt patres non ſolum nihil peccando, verumetiam ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtè ſingula peragendo manifeſtum res è filijs exhibeant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplar, vt in corum vitam ſe vt in ſpeculum intueantur.</hi> Before all thinges it is néedefull, that fathers ſhould ſhew themſelues vnto theyr children as a manifeſt patterne or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, not onely be not ſinning, but alſo by doing al things honeſtlie, that they may looke into their liues, and peruſe themſelues as in a glaſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:22657:8"/>
Ariſtotle being aſket in what ſort we ought to ſhew our ſelues to our frendes, marie ſaith he, in that ſorte as wee woulde wiſhe that they ſhoulde ſhew themſelues to vs. If this point pertaineth to frendſhip, much rather to paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, who finde it a harder matter to enfourme their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren well, then it is to beget them. For according as they are trayned vp by their parentes wordes and examples, ſuch wil they proue to be, after the prouerbial verſe. <hi>Arbor naturam dat fructibus atque figuram.</hi> Fruites are woont to take their ſhape and nature of the tree.</p>
               <p>All things are deriued from the worthier parts whether they be good or euill, and the vertue of an honeſt man or good Father, is like to the ſauour of muſke which impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his goodnes to others that buy not of it. Of this minde appeared to bée that vertuous Prince Lewes of France, called the good King, who leaſt his eldeſt Sonne Charles the Dolphin ſhoulde bée vnmindefull of thoſe thinge which he taught him by good example in his life time, at the time of his death lefte theſe preceptes in writing to bee deliuered vnto him, of likelyhood as a Codicill or parte of his will, which Chriſtian like counſailes are worthy to bee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and remembred eſpecially by them that ſuccéede in nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, authority, or generoſity.</p>
               <p>The aduertiſementes were theſe.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> Firſt yéelde an account of thy ſinnes diligently, vſing the helpe and ſound counſaile of foure wiſe and well learned men that will not bee afraide to rebuke and controll thee,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> Serue God deuoutly in the Church.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> Be conuerſant with vertuous men and ſuch as liue in good order.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> Ruffians and ſuch as haue no feare of God, let them be farre off from thée.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi> Be ready and willing to heare good counſaile bée it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly or openly.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6</hi> Let not blaſphemers of God and deſpiſers of holy thinges eſcape from thée vnrebuked or vnpuniſhed.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7</hi> Towardes all Chriſtians be thou a ſeuere and an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right
<pb facs="tcp:22657:8"/>Iudge not fauouring one parte more then the other.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8</hi> If thou muſt needes make warre, be a protector of Chriſtes Church and all innocents.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9</hi> Be not the meanes of ſwearing and forſwering, but rather forbid it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Laſtly my Sonne I exhort and pray ſhée, I leauing this worlde before thée, that thou wilt haue a godly, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and dutifull regard towards mee.</p>
               <p>The precepts be ſuch as it may bee wiſhed there were more practiſers of the like.</p>
               <p>The wiſe and vertuous Prince ſeemed a carefull and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent follower of ghoſtly counſaile, and namely of this out of Eccleſiaſticus. <hi>Who ſo informeth and teacheth hys Sonne, greeueth the enemy, and before his friends he may haue ioy of him, though the Father die, yet is he as though he were not dead, for he hath lefte one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him that is like him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The biſhop of Auguſta in his booke <hi>De via Regia,</hi> hath this aduertiſment vnto parents. When thy Sonne (ſaieth hee) ſhall aske thee which be the auncient wayes, thou ſhalt tell him of the auncient faith, and of the holy and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued life and good workes of the Patriarkes, Prophets, Apoſtles, and others the ſeruaunts and freindes of God, who by the true and ſincere faith, raiſed the dead, cleanſed the leaporous, and reſtored ſight to the blinde.</p>
               <p>The like Chriſtian and religious leſſons ought to be taught as readily as any worldly inſtructions.</p>
               <p>That which a man ſoweth that he ſhall reape.</p>
               <p>Let the Father giue good examples and hee ſhall reape the fruite thereof, on the life, maners, and proſperity of his children.</p>
               <p>Let him bee milde and louing, and he ſhall taſte of the loue of God.</p>
               <p>Let himſelfe not be ſtubborne againſt the wil of God and lawes, and he ſhal finde it recompenced in the duetie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of his children.</p>
               <p>Let him forgiue the offences of reaſonable ſonnes,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22657:9"/>and he ſhall ouercome their frowardneſſe and ill diſpoſition if the Philoſophers words be true, which ſaieth, <hi>Filium be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolentia patris meliorem facit,</hi> that is, The beneuolent &amp; fauouralbe dealing of the Father, maketh the ſonne better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. That Fathers ought not to giue ill examples.</head>
               <p>AMongs the Lacedemonians, if two brethren fell at ſtrife betwéene themſelues, the Magiſtrate awarded that the Father ſhoulde be puniſhed: for that either he was the cauſe of it, or did not preuent it before: or remedy it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For they thought the young men were to be pardoned. And if they offended by the intemperance of youth, their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was to bée blamed, whoſe authority ought to forſée and prouide, that no ſtrife or debate riſe betwéen his ſons. And therefore a Father ought to bée very carefull in nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and maintaining naturall loue and concord in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and in any wiſe not to ſuffer any ſparke of hatred to enter into their heartes, leaſt it kindle a fire in their breſt: much leſſe ought he to caſt in coales of diſcorde among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſelfe by any vnkinde or iniurious examples of dealing. For the ſtate of a family if it bée in due order, is like to a frame of ioyning worke or building, wherein if ſome one peece bée out of his place, it tendeth to a diſordering of all the reſt, and one diſorder following an other, all becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out of ioynt, and falleth vnto a confuſion verie diſprai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable. Therefore it ſéemes this ſaying of the holy Ghoſt is not of light regarded. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ae dantibus malum exemplum:</hi> woe vnto them that giue ill examples, the grieuouſneſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the holy Doctor Saint Auguſtine rather augmenteth then diminiſheth, when he ſaieth that a man may ſlay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by his examples.</p>
               <p>Euen as the Father beginneth ſo it is like the ſonne will procéede, for as the Philoſopher ſaieth, <hi>Amat vnuſquiſque ſequi vitam parentum:</hi> Euerie man loueth to doe as his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did before him. And as Seueca ſaieth, <hi>Ther is no
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22657:9"/>wicked act, but the example of it hath been followed.</hi> If the Father neglect the expreſſe will of God, who would and ought to ſtrike a ſtroke, as well in the ordering of his family, as in the directing of his life, or if hee ſwarue from the vſage of the wiſeſt or beſt forte of parentes preferring his owne fancy or wilfull conceite before all other reaſon, the Sonne by his example will doe the like. If the Father by an example of iniurie or diſorder, giueth an entry to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim of minde, and hatred of heart in his family, the Sonne of proneſſe vnto euill, and to imitation of his Fathers ſteps will not bee ſo ready to extinguiſh and quenche this kindled miſchiefe, but rather adde ſtickes thereto and augment it, by obſeruing a badde tradition from his aunceſtors, paſſing that iniurie ouer to others, which he receiued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: namely when by want of good example in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, the regarde and awe of lawe and good order is taken away, and a gappe opened to the actions of infidelitie and inhumanitie.</p>
               <p>I ſay infidelity ſeeing the life of a Chriſtian conſiſteth of two partes: vidz. faith and good workes, of his faith I wil not iudge: but let his good workes bée the meeteſt triall which are commanded and required, to the glory of God, to the profite of our neighbour, or to taming of the fleſhe, and brideling of the fleſhly appetites.</p>
               <p>Here is no glory of God regarded, where his will ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no place: and as little good to come to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, where he vouchſafeth ſo much hurt to his owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>What ſhould I ſay in this caſe? aboue all the fleſhly will and appetite is followed and preferred without forſight of the inconueniences to come thereby, or any indeuour to auoide them.</p>
               <p>And ſurely if either wée were ſo good Chriſtians as wée pretend, or did carrie in vs the minde of naturall and kinde parentes,: or but the conſtant and heartie affection of a true friende, wée ſhoulde be as ready to make haſt to put out and extinguiſhe an iniurie, as wée woulde bee to put
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22657:10"/>out fire, taking holde in our neighbours houſe and ready to flame forth and conſume it. For if an iniury bee not redreſſed and taken away in the beginning, it groweth and increaſeth to infinite rage of furie.</p>
               <p>But what ſhoulde I ſpeake of theſe thinges, that bee matters of Chriſtian charity, and workes of faith: where vnto men are not ſo readily inclined to performe them, as to talke of them, bidding him blowe the coale that is a colde: euerie man poſteth it ouer and thinketh it pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not to him, becauſe it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth as much to others. And therefore in ſome places of Chriſtendome, theſe and the like offices of Chriſtian charitie, are appointed vnto ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry companies or fraternities of men.</p>
               <p>Vnto one ſorte is committed the care and regarde of priſoners vppon life and death: that by their trauaile and charitable induſtrie, the wretched and infortunat crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, may make a happie ende and recompence their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and miſfortune, with the bliſfull eſtate of peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and clenſed ſoules.</p>
               <p>Vnto others is committed the charge of reconciling open or priuy enemies and aduerſaries.</p>
               <p>Some are appointed to be workers of reconcilement betweene men and their vnlawful wiues, liuing a parte without iuſt cauſe of ſeperation or diuorce.</p>
               <p>Others there hee that are enioined to trauaile and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade women of looſe and lewde life, to remember themſelues and their ſoules health, and after their going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray to returne home vnto the honeſty of their parentes and duetie of good Chriſtians, and from thenceforth to liue an honeſt and vnſuſpected life.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like bee weake and ruinous places ofte in the walles of ſome ſtates, that might bee repaired, if charitie were not ſo colde, and the workes of faith ſo much decayed in apparaunce, chiefly through ill examples giuen: whereof the account will bee ſomewhat heauy and grieuous to diſcharge. Aske the Lawiers, <hi>De iniuriis &amp; damno dato.</hi> If any man open a Ceſterne or maketh a pit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22657:10"/>and doe not couer it, and in the mean ſpace an Oxe, Cow, or ſome other cattle faleth therein, I thinke they will ſay hee is bounde to make ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>O but howe much more if the ſoules of thy children fall by thy ill example. If wee looke into the bequeathed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xamples of ſome Fathers, what a Chaoe and diſorder might there bee noted, either wrought by their peruerſe dealing, or by the malice and vnhappineſſe of a woman peruerting al. Strifes and iarres lefte in ſteede of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accorde: hatred and maliciouſnes occupying the place of brotherly loue, wrangling and wreſting one from another, in ſtéede of helping and comforting.</p>
               <p>Socrates did bid young men to looke in a glaſſe, to the ende that finding themſelues wel formed and of good ſhape, they might beware to doe any thing that was vnſéemely for that naturall grace, and if they were of ill ſhape, they might endeuour to ſupply and recompence their bodily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with ſome vertue and qualitie of the minde. Euen ſo would I wiſhe that ſome parentes ſhoulde looke into the example of the beſt ſort as into a glaſſe, and it the finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues deformed and blemiſhed by any vnkinde actions or naughtie examples, they may recompence it with beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Fatherlie dealings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. That Fathers ought not to prouoke their children to wrath and diſobedience.</head>
               <p>COtys King of Thrace a man inclined by nature to bee angry and wrathfull, and therewithall a ſeuere corrector of ſuch as chaunced to offende or committe a fault in ſeruing him: on a time, a ſtraunger brought him for a preſent certaine fine veſſelles of earth glaſed, very cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly wrought, and delicate to beholde. He rewarded the bringer, but ſtraight wayes caſt the veſſelles againſt the wall. Others about him maruailing that he did ſo, marry
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22657:11"/>quoth he, I doe it, becauſe they ſhall not make mee angry with them that ſhall happen to breake them. He knewe his owne diſeaſe, and therefore wiſely preuented the hurt and diſpleaſure likely to happen, by auoyding the meanes and occaſion. Now for as much as wrath, is an immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perturbation, that hardeneth the affection and maketh the forces of a man violent, being ſometimes the cauſe of manſlaughter, and ſometimes of other calamitie, yea ſome times the originall and beginning of treaſon, and if it flie not ſo high the beſt that commeth of it is diſquiet, loſſe, or diſcredite: who would not by poſſible meanes auoyde the prouoking of an affection ſo troubleſome and ſo bad in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans houſe or with them with whom he hath nothing to doe? much rather ought he to kéepe ſuch a gueſt out of his owne houſe which is the greateſt enemie a man can haue: For it maketh a man that ſhould ſéeme reaſonable and of decent behauiour and doings, to ſhew like a trée ſet a fire which is like neuer after to beare good fruit, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he may be likened to a barke or ſhippe ſubiected to the rage of a cruell ſtorme, and thereby in great hazard of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing. The Apoſtle S. Paule <hi>Hebr. 12.</hi> knowing ſuch an infirmitie to beare ſway in many perſons, gaue a gheſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admonition to preuent it, ſaying: <hi>See that no man be deſtitute of the grace of God, and that no roote of bitternes ſpring vp &amp; trouble you, for thereby many be defiled.</hi> But Valerius Marimus excéedeth ſome what the modeſtie of this ſentence, and ſayth, that wrath and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred doe ſtirre vp great floudes in the heartes of men, for whom ſuch diſguiſing paſſions be moſt vnſéemely as may appeare by this verſe of the Poet:</p>
               <q>Candida pax homines trux decet iraferas:</q>
               <p>Sure it is that one man is néereſt kin vnto an other, how may a parent be as a ſtranger or aduerſarie to his owne ſonne? No man hateth his owne fleſh: <hi>Ephe.</hi> I meane ſuch as be in the fleſh or liue after the fleſh: except you will ſpeake of Martyrs and ſuch as ſet little of the fleſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is an other thing preferred with them. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22657:11"/>yet hatred of the fleſh in them is rather to be vnderſtoode of the vices, than of their owne fleſhe. Saint Paule knowing the vndiſcreteneſſe of many parentes and the ill ſucceſſe and fruiteleſſe ende of their bitter ſpéeches and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent dealing with their children, was not vnmindefull of the childrens cauſe for the fathers inſtruction in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Col. <hi>3.</hi> Fathers ſayth he, beware howe yée reuile or rigorouſly deale with your children leaſt yée put them into a deſperate minde, therefore wee may ſay it is good to tender as much as you may the preſeruation of kindely loue and good will betwixt yée, euen in your childrens tender yeares, and whiles they be yet vnder your lawe and correction, giue no occaſion of diſloue or griefe taking for vnkinde wordes or dealing. Kéepe out of your houſe theſe fire brandes of wrath and anger, which prouooke vnto diſobedience in wordes or déedes. But much rather let not you infirmitie or maliciouſneſſe, bee expreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them of more than rype yeares: for there an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe is conceiued more déepely. Remember you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende not againſt the eight commandement which ſayeth, <hi>Non loquaris contra proxim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m tuum falſum testimonium,</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſpeake falſe witneſſe againſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. If by your rayling and bitter wordes yée prouooke your children to wrath and from wrath to diſobedience, ſome Doctors interpret extreame ſpéeches and prouocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to mortall falling out, ſo ſtraightly &amp; ſeuerely that they ſay and write, <hi>Nihil interest verum ferro an verbo occidas,</hi> There is no difference whether you ſlay with weapon or by worde, and therefore ſéeing the amendment of ill man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners muſt come from your ſelues by your good example of tolleration or forbearing, ſet the coldeneſſe and experienced iudgement of your yeares, and the mildneſſe of that nature which pertayneth to Parents againſt their broyling heate and raſhnes, <hi>Ex duobus contrariis fit optimum tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum.</hi> Of two contraries (ſayth Philoſophie) is made a goodly temperature. And no doubt the faults of children are ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ner cured and reformed by gentle wordes and milde
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22657:12"/>perſwaſions, than by furious fits of anger and violence. It you ſée faultes and imperfections in your children, eyther they tooke them of you or elſe you haue as badde in your ſelues: Crates the Philoſopher helde it was impoſſible to finde any man that is not faulty in ſome pointes, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring man generally to a Pome granate when he is at beſt, which from thencefoorth hath alwayes ſome rotten graines like vnto mens faultes and ill qualities, which be not cured by wrath and euill wordes, but by counſaile and friendly admonition. And herein a father ought to ſhewe him ſelfe like a Phiſition, who doth not vſe to handle his cures with raging and rayling, but rather bethinketh him what hée may miniſter beſt for their health, finding for the moſt part euery intemperate humour or cauſe beſt to be cured by his contrarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. That Fathers ought to deale kindely and faythfully and not preiudicially or fraudulently towards their children.</head>
               <p>A Certaine friend admoniſhed Ageſilans the Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian King (as yet but newly come to the dignitie) that he would now remember his preeminent ſtate, and lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide ſome part of his hard manner of liuing, and vſe ſome more maieſtie and delicateneſſe in his dyet, lodging and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrell: he anſwered, nay not ſo, I will be alwayes one manner of man becauſe fortune is ſo chaungeable. Such was the conſtancie and faithfull heart of this wiſe Prince towardes his ſubiects, that hee could hardly be brought to any inwarde or outwarde alteration, though the chaunge of his eſtate, did in a manner forbid him to continue his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer courſe. But this is alwayes founde to be true: looke where there is loue, there is alſo fayth and truſtineſſe. Hee was nowe become the vniuerſall Parent of his Countrie, and therefore néedes muſt hée loue, and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the name of a louing Parent, howe may hée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22657:12"/>vnfaithfull.</p>
               <p>Truly there be many, in whome the lawe of nature and the loue of GOD both take ſo little holde, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſo ſmall and ſlender effectes of kindeneſſe or chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that they may ſcarce ſhrowde or ſhew themſelues vnder the name of true friends or friendſhip: ſuch is their hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, diſſembling in wordes, and fraude in dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. I will not ſay, that ſuch be counterfeitors of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, becauſe that is a fault woorſe then the forging of falſe money. For he that taketh a little forged coyne for good, his dammage is not great: but to take or haue a fained friend in ſteade of one true, conſtant, and faithfull, the hurte muſt néedes bée great, and the griefe more. Well may we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine with the Poet in this verſe:</p>
               <q>Heu quam parua fides reperitur nunc apud ciues?</q>
               <p>Truſtie faithfulneſſe in many parents decayeth, whoſe wordes, by the rule and example of good men, ought to bée as much woorthie in credite and accompt, as the othes of ſtrangers. Such as in their workes and examples declare themſelues inconſtant in fatherly loue, and ſo double in their actions, are iuſtly meaſured by this rule of Salomon Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs the twelfe, A true mouth is euer conſtant, but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling tongue is ſoone changed. O howe ſoone are many fathers altered from the naturall loue and inward affection towardes their children, if they fall once to be entertained wyth the gléekes of gallant gloſers, and to bee wantonlie wrapped in loue and liking of newe ſpowſes of Bigamie. What will they not doe to pleaſe their appetites? Whom will they not hate to gaine their diſſembled fauours? The waight of a Kingdome coulde not alter or change Ageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus from béeing one manner of man vnto hys familie, and ſuch as were vnder him: but the waight of a woman can counterpoiſe woonderfully wyth ſome of theſe, and weigh them quite from the ground of nature and honeſt conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. But no maruell, ſith it is of olde experience, that loue maketh great alteration and conqueſt, according vnto this plaine Latine verſe:</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22657:13"/>
Caecat amor mentes, &amp; interdumſapientes.</q>
               <p>Loue blindeth mindes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad ſometimes makes wſſe men to dote. Saint Bernarb writing vnto his parents, ſaieth, He can not come néere vnto wiſedome that geueth himſelfe to ſléepe or to dote: and they doe ſléepe or dote, that doe giue themſelues ouer to ſenſualitie: daily forgoing good counſell and gifts of grace which is the beſt treſure they haue. Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſléeping in Dalidas lappe loſt his ſtrength. May thoſe huſhands or parentes trowe you be déemed rulers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their forces, that with ſo ſmall reſiſtance yéelde them to the dominion and tyranny of amorous follie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſhipwracke of their reaſon, and whatſoeuer vertue and valure is in them beſides? But of ſuch lither and flerible folke it is likelie it will at length fare wyth them as it did with Amon the ſonne of Dauid, who was ſo in loue wyth Thamar his owne ſiſter, that he fained himſelfe to be ſicke, and to ſurfet with loue till he had defiled hir, &amp; from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth he neuer loued her ſo ardently, as nowe he beganne to hate and loath her. So, when theſe men through the light of reaſon, and illumining of grace, ſhall perceiue in hows great a labyrinth of errour and wrong perſwaſion of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens will and wilineſſe they haue wandered contrarie to reaſon and ſound aduiſe, or as ſoone as GOD ſhall touch their heart with grace and repentance of their carnall follie and immoderate ſeruing of the fleſh, they will beginne to remember themſelues in the duetie of kind parents.</p>
               <p>By the Councell Gangrenſe it was decréede, that if any man (though it were by occaſion of geuing ouer the world, and entring into religion) did neglect to haue a due care for his children, as well for the godly enforming of them, as alſo touching that which pertained to them otherwiſe, <hi>ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema ſit,</hi> Let him be accurſed. But we muſt thinke great difference betwéene neglecting them through a certaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious contemning of worldly thinges, and the caſting of them off, by reaſon of the appetite of newe loue. But yet there is a much more difference to be vnderſtoode betwéen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> negligent regarde, and carefull reſpecte had towardes chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22657:13"/>or ſuch as be vnder our charge. Which ill example before recited and reprooued, may wel be counteruailed with this contrarie. Epaminondas a famous Duke or Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Grecians, going foorth to an exploite of warre, his wife deſired him to looke well vnto himſelfe. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, This is an aduiſe fit for other men, and not for me: for he that taketh on him a charge as I doe, his part is to looke well to the ſafetie of them that be vnder him, ſéeing manie are more to be reſpected then one?</p>
               <p>If we wil not with this biſhoplike Duke preferre the ſafetie and better worldly ſtate of our children and familie, before the regarde and ſatiſfying of our carnall deſire and wanton appetite, ſo vnſeaſonable or ſo inconuenient, yet at leaſt let us reſpect the health of their ſoules, before the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and vaine loue of any earthly perſon. Diogenes that was ſo poore in worldly ſubſtance, and ſo rich in wiſedome, and giftes of grace certifieth vs, that God loueth them that be diſobedient to their priuate luſtes. And to ſay the trueth, ſo a man ought to be: if not for ſo high a cauſe, yet of this baſer reſpect in auoyding hurts and inconueniences ſenſibly perceiued to enſue to himſelfe, and his firſt children. Which in déede were the parte of a faithfull friend compared vnto golde or ſiluer. And what faith, I pray you, ought there to be betwéene parents and their children, where we muſt acknowledge a bond of nature that bindes both parts? The law rule is, In vaine doth any man require faith or promiſe to be kept by him, to whom himſelfe refuſeth to kéepe faith. But in ſuch a caſe the diſhoneſtie will be the more, if the ſtronger ſhew himſelf the weaker, in breaking firſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for ſundry reſpectes worldly and diuine, it is of all good men to be wiſhed or aduiſed, that Parents attempt not firſt the breaking of this band chiefly to their owne harme, but euen as the ſight of a ſcarre in an other mans face geueth them warning to beware of wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds lighting on themſelues, ſo they beholding or remembring other mens errours, and euil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es in this behalfe paſt, the ſame by Gods grace and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance may cauſe them to take the better héede, in auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22657:14"/>the like miſchiefes of their owne or their familie to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Of fathers or parentes, who diſpoſe their goods or lands after their priuate will and fancie without due regarde of nature, reaſon, and order.</head>
               <p>THe gladſome and ioyfull temperature of the morning was long ſince halfe forgotten: the heighth of the Sunne is in declination: the heate of the daie is paſt: the euening draweth on, euerie creature beginneth to go vnto his reſt. Man that hath paſſed the whole courſe of this worlde, which is, for the moſt parte, equally mirte wyth ſorrowe and ioy, what hath hée laboured or ſpent his time for, if he finde not reſt at his ending? As for the thinges wherein hée delighted, hée findeth them all but vaine, and after alittle while, are quite vaniſhed, ſaue onely his good déedes and his bad. Theſe bide by him, and will not light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſeparated from him. Penance, or repentance ought now to be moſt in his purpoſe: his negligence therein will now appeare.</p>
               <p>Night commeth on, and as the Apoſtle ſaieth vnto the Galathians chap. <hi>6. <hi>Me oporter operari cum dies eſt, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nit enim nox quando operari nemo poteſt.</hi>
                  </hi> I muſt worke whiles it is day, for no man can worke when night commeth.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be the day neuer ſo long,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>at length it will ring to Euen ſong.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>But who is ſure to make out a whole dayes worke, and to enioy the fruition of mans common age? ſéeing it is ſaid in Eccl. <hi>9. <hi>Neſcit homo finem ſuum, ſed ſicut aues capiun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur laeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; piſces ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o.</hi>
                  </hi> Man knoweth not his ende, but is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtaken euen as bir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es be wyth the ſnare, and fiſhes wyth the hooke. Euery man is iudged wiſe or fooliſh by the maner of his ending: for one day denieth and controlleth an other, but the laſt day geueth indgement of al the reſt A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:22657:14"/>at his ending hath two wayes to looke vnto: Backewards to his ſinnes, offences, and negligences paſt, and Forwards by ſetting a good order in his familie, and well diſpoſing of things for peace, quietneſſe, and other godly effects to come. His life time, good health, and beſt remembrance, is fitteſt for the one, and the eueningtide of his iourny in this world, is not too late for the other. Pythagoras ſaide, that Golde is tryed by fire, A woman by Gold (that is, whether ſhée be good or not) and man by woman, viz. whether hée bée con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly naturall and well minded towardes his children, and good to his owne ſoule. For he that neglecteth his children, as ſaith the diuine Poet Horace, depriueth him ſelfe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie. By the want of children his ſhape, phiſnomy, name, and memoriall periſheth: fith in the renuing and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of the worke of nature, the ſame is freſhly renued and maintained. Wherein, I pray you, is the effecte of true friendſhip laſting after death, better and more ſurely to be verefied, then betwéene a kinde parent deceaſed, and his children? which by an Embleme may be reſembled to a drie or dead trée garniſhed and adorned wyth a gréene and well proſpering Vine, and ſpecially by ſuch as reſemble the parent, not onely in phiſnomie (which is the beſt aſſured to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of true dealing) but alſo in ſteps of honeſty and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towardnes.</p>
               <p>King Alexander was of that humane and princely mind, that he would ſay: A mans riches are no where ſo well laid vp and ſafely kept, as in the handes of his friendes. Where ſhould a parent then beſtowe them, but on his owne ſoule, or vpon the life and reléeuing of his children? Shall he now giue eare to any couetous or exceſſiue requeſt of a woman? Shall her deceitfull teares make him to ſwarue from the minde and purpoſe of a kinde father, and the couenant of nature it ſelfe? No not ſo. Hée muſt nowe lay aſide fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and ouercome his owne will. And there is no greater and more laudable victorie, then for a man to vanquiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by yéelding vnto the reaſon and authoritie of nature, law, and the will of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:22657:15"/>
For ſure it is, that the loue of a couetous woman would long agone haue ended, if goodes had failed: and to ſaie trueth, for the moſt parte, ſo doth the loue of the man domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, if not vtterly ende, when beaurie decayeth. Shall I regarde her teares? No, for they be of two ſortes, the one of griefe, the other of deceite. For a little goodneſſe ſhée will looke forſooth to haue a great rewarde, little remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring herſelfe what euill ſhée hath doone, and had neuer any chaſtiſement for it. As the holie Doctor ſaieth, he that hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the euill, hurteth the good: but we may ſay, he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richeth a ſtepmother, helpeth a ſtranger and hindereth his owne: yea perhappes fourdeth his wealth vnto his enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and ſcarcitie vnto them of his owne fleſhe and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring. Sée héere the peruerſeneſſe of manie men in their like dealinges, by following fancie, and obeying theyr owne will, wherein it ſéemeth the wiſe Philoſopher Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to was nothing deceyued when hée ſayde, Hée that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to followe his will, is neare the wrath of GOD. For the brideling, reſtraining, or moderating of which will God by his Miniſters héere in earth hath let an order by ciuil, canon, and nationall lawes.</p>
               <p>There bee ſundrie perſons that can not alienate theyr goodes, nor make willes. Likewiſe there be thinges of ſome nature or qualitie in the poſſeſſing and propertie of them, that they may not be alienated or tranſiated vnto the commoditie or propertie of an other, according vnto the will, fancie and fauouring of him that laſt poſſeſſed them. Alſo there be ſome Countries and Citties, which, eyther forbid willes to be made, or elſe by their Cuſtome doe make and appoint willes for men, becauſe they ſhall not followe their owne will. The prodigall perſon; the bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>man, the guiltie of treaſon, nor the approoued hereticke can not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any thing by their w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</p>
               <p>By the conſtruction of the Diuines, who is not prodigall and a miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ponder of thoſe giftes, which. GOD hath beſtowed vppon him? Who is not a bondman? <hi>Qui facit peccatum ſeruus eſt peccati,</hi> Iohn the eight Chapiter.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22657:15"/>
                  <hi>He that committeth ſinne is the ſeruant or bondman of ſinne,</hi> and to confirme that ſaying more plantely take theſe wordes of Saint Peter <hi>1.2. <hi>A quo quis ſuperatus eſt eius ſernus eſt.</hi>
                  </hi> Of whome ſoeuer any man is ouercome, to him is he bound. The vnfaithfull or miſbeléeuing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, is hardly charged with treaſon committed againſt the celeſtiall Emperour. And therefore hath Saint Auguſtine <hi>In li. de ouibus. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>igilate hereties audite a paſtore teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pacis: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enite adpacem: iraſcimini Chriſtianis Jmpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoribus quia teſtamenta veſtra valere noluerunt in domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus veſtris: dolor eſt: admonitio eſt, non dum damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, dicit tibi Deus noli fraudes querere. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>is ſtare teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum tuum? Stet in te meum.</hi> The thinges before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned that may not bee tranſlated or beſtowed after the will of the poſſeſſors, are the eccleſiaſtical goods and fruits. For ſéeing all Churchly authority is to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fie and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, a clerke might not by eccleſiaſticall conſtitutions, make his wil otherwiſe then according to their order and vocation. For hee might not enrich his carnall brethren or kinſfolke, although hee might giue them <hi>victum &amp; veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> that is, foode and apparell, by reaſon that the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical things were called and reputed <hi>oblationes: quia do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino offeruntur.</hi> And therefore ſaide thoſe lawes <hi>non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent in aliis vſibus quam eccleſiaſticis vel chriſtianorum fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum indigentium conuerti: quia vota ſunt fidelium &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia peccatorum &amp; patrimonia pauperum.</hi> The ſaying of Saint Ambroſe is ſomewhat fearefull vppon this pointe, As riches (ſaieth he) to ſome men (through miſbeſtowing of them) be an an occaſion of damnation, ſo in good mens hands (by their well beſtowing) they bee helpes of vertue. The cauſe I haue thus digreſſed and mencioned of theſe matters, which ſéeme not plainely retaining to this point of ſantaſticall or wilful willing and diſpoſing of the parents ſubſtance or goods, is partly to induce and prooue that the freewill and fancy of ſome ſortes of men are reſtrained by the lawes Eccleſiaſtical and Imperiall in all countries. But of all ſortes of men at leaſt preſcribed and bounded in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22657:16"/>ſome Countries.</p>
               <p>Alſo by all lawes and in all Countries, that is a rule of reaſon to bee regarded among Chriſtian men. <hi>Who ſo hath power to diſpoſe goods, ought rather to haue right conſideration towardes the cauſes to bee reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in them that ſtand at his deuotion then to hys owne power.</hi> Sith it is the ſaying of a wiſe man <hi>quanto liceat tanto libeat minus,</hi> As the goods of the church in time paſt were thought not properly to pertaine to lay perſons, ſo the goods of any parent cannot temporally be beſtowed on any perſons more properly, then vppon his owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren according to order of their age, and as the wiſeſt and beſt ſorte of men are wont to doe.</p>
               <p>Now to touch ſomewhat the duety of good and natural children, it is to witte, that this worde <hi>filius</hi> or <hi>filia</hi> ſonne or daughter commeth of the word <hi>Philos</hi> in Gréeke, which is loue or louer. And that ſonne or daughter which expreſſeth not loue towardes the parent, as well when he is departed this worlde, as whiles hee is preſent, I wotte not which is worſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in him, either his vngodlineſſe or his ingratitude, but ſéeing ingratitude is vngodlineſſe, it were good that children know it well that they may the better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noid the blot thereof. It is a vice which in ſome good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men wealths hath beene puniſhed as readily as any others if it were in the higheſt degrée.</p>
               <p>The firſt and loweſt degrée of vnthankfulneſſe is, not to requite a benefite.</p>
               <p>The ſecond to diſpraiſe or diſdaine it in reſpecte of the thing.</p>
               <p>The thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to forget a benefit.</p>
               <p>But the fourth degrée is rendring euill for good.</p>
               <p>The Storkes for the naturall kindneſſe receiued, will beare their parent on their backe when hee is olde, and féeds him if hee bee not able to ſturre abroade for his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. In hye Caſtile theſe patternes of kinde paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage are to bee ſéene, breeding in the toppe almoſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie Church, tower or ſtéeple: of likelyhoode fauoured
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22657:16"/>and foſtéred there of purpoſe for that leſions ſake, which that bird can teach man.</p>
               <p>And although the dutie of children is to helpe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour their parents if they ſhould néede, yet by lawe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they are appointed rather to receiue benefites of their Parents, than to giue vpwardes. For well you wot that loue, benefites, and all other good thinges are woont to deſcende. Lawe will not that the father bee the ſonnes heyre, but willeth rather that the father ſhould reſtore that to his poſteritie which himſelfe receiued from his aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſith no guift or token of beneuolence is more fitter for children to beſtowe, or for the parentes and benefactors to receiue, than the benefite of heartie and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayer, it ſhall not be much amiſſe for all dutifull children to remember their debt in that point after the forme of the Grammer caſe rule.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>Nominatino.</label> Firſt to pray for your ſelfe that you may be ſo ghoſtly ſtrengthened that you fall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot into mortall ſinne by frailtie, and that you may haue right knowledge of God by fayth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Genitiuo.</label> For your Progenitors as Parentes, brothers, ſiſters, and kinſfolke.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Datiuo.</label> For your benefactors.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Accuſatiuo.</label> For your enemies.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocatiuo.</label> For them that be in errour or infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, that they may come to the right way of their ſaluation.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Ablatiuo.</label> For them that be abſent.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:22657:17"/>
Saint Paule vnto Timoth. ſayth, <hi>If any man haue not a care for them of his owne familie, hee is an infidell.</hi> And therefore he ſayth in an other place, <hi>Si quid patitur v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num membrum compatiuntur omnia membra. <hi>If one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be in paine all the reſt be not without anguiſh or griefe.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>O good God, who is ſo harde hearted that will not haue compaſſion or chriſtian regarde on his parent, kinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or friend, if he thought him in the caſe of ſtraight im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment or if he wiſt he were in any miſerable or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſtate where prayer or friendſhip might helpe or doe him good? The ſtate of a man in miſbeléefe, infidelitie, or ſecuritie in ſinning without tokens of repentance, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment is daungerous God wot, and not without néede of aſſiſtance by hearty and earneſt praier of faithfull friends and naturall children.</p>
               <p>For we muſt beléeue that God will puniſh ſinne, and all other impietie: elſe why doth he threaten ſinners ſo ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by that example in the <hi>5.</hi> of Matth. <hi>Amen: dico vobis non exies inde donec ſolueris nouiſsimum quadrantem:</hi> that is, <hi>Verely I ſay vnto you, thou ſhalt not depart thence vntill thou haſt payd the vttermoſt farthing.</hi> I ſée not how you can pertake with parents, brothers, or kinſfolke in nature, and haue no féeling of their ſinefull life, erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous condition, or other their pitifull ſtate in your compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and commiſeration. But euen as you deale towards them vnto whom ye owe any charitable or naturall dutie, ſo ſhall they ſerue you at whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euotion you ſhall happen to ſtande. Then with the ſame meaſure ye meate vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it is to be doubted, will be meaſured to you againe, ſomewhat according to the wordes of <hi>Naomie</hi> to <hi>Ruth</hi> ſaying: <hi>cap. 1. <hi>Faciat vobiſcum Deus miſericordiam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſicut feciſtis cum mortuis.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22657:17"/>
            <head>The ſeconde part bewrayeth the malignitie of a Stepdame, the monſtrous transfourming of the Father, and the often calamitie of the firſt children.</head>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Of the vngentle dealing of ſome ſtepmothers towards their husbandes firſt children.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen a Father ſo little remembreth or regardeth the bond of nature and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dealing of a kinde parent, that hée forbeareth not to bring into his family a Stepdame, he can not doe a thing of better liking to his foes (if he haue any ſuch that foreſée it) and wiſh ill betiding vnto him and his. For what may bring vnto a Citie or houſe more harme or inconuenience, than diſcord, which diuideth a houſe and maketh of one Cittie two? Inteſtine diuiſion is euer counted worſe than the malignitie of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde foes, as warre is accounted worſe than peace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In diſcord no man prayſeth the Lorde,</hi> As witneſſeth Saint Ambroſe. What bleſſing then doe they depriue vs of, that take away peace and good agréement. Well may ſome children complaine with the Poet in this caſe, who ſayth in his pleaſant méeter:
<q>
                     <l>Sunt tria gaudia, pax, ſapientia, copia rerum,</l>
                     <l>Haec tria diluit, haec tria deſtruit ars mulierum.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This Stepmother by the pretence and name of mariage
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22657:18"/>is called in Latine, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor, quaſi vnxor,</hi> a <hi>Wife,</hi> as it were <hi>an Annoynter,</hi> for that the new married Spowſe in olde time at her firſt comming home was wont to annoynt the poaſtes and principall partes of the houſe in token that ſhe came to heale and cure all faultes or to remooue ſorrow and to plant and encreaſe gladneſſe in the place. But I frowe this our Stepdame at this day annoynteth not with the oyle of gladneſſe, nor with the vnction of the holy ſpirite, by whom ſo much ſorrowe is many times brought in, and ſo many vngodly effectes wrought and encreaſed. Call yée this annoynting? ſhe annoynteth in déede: but vnhappie be thoſe poſtes &amp; parts of the houſe where ſhe laieth her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckie handes, as <hi>Euripides</hi> ſayth, <hi>Stepdames ſeeldome with and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke any good to their hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bands children,</hi> and too much experience teacheth, they be their vtter ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, and cauſe of confuſion. For what be their ordinary practiſes in manner as principles of then partment pollicy? For ſooth firſt and chiefely to bring their huſbandes children out of conceipt &amp; fauour, to frame the matter ſo, that they may be counted diſobedient &amp; by that meanes to wipe from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all good will. They thinke they muſt not ſuffer ſo much a let and blocke in their way to their huſbandes wealth as the bulworke of loue and concord. This is a great eye ſore and hardly tollerable with them. This they imagine they muſt aſſault and aſſay to batter and beat downe by the beſt engine they haue: they can bend againſt it Cannon ſhot of great diſpleaſure, they are ſufficiently furniſhed with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a malicious and wicked ſpirite, nor want they any ſhot of quarrelous deuiſes to perce &amp; ſhake this poore rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of kindly good will with kindled ſtrife and contention. Of this kind they can ſharpe them new ſupplies from time to time, ſpecially if they haue their huſbandes well tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to their humour and appetite, then may it be ſayd of the poore enchanted men, as we find it in the Pſalme: <hi>Os ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, &amp; non l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quuntur: aures, &amp; non audiunt: oculos, &amp; non vident. <hi>They haue mouthes, and ſpeake not: cares, and may not heare: eyes, and will not ſee.</hi>
                  </hi> They ſtande in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22657:18"/>dread and awe they wot who muſt be foothed in all thinges or elſe will followe but colde kiſſing, ſhe claimeth all the loue and goodwill to her ſelfe, and if ſhe vnderſtoode Latine ſhe would chuſe this good verſe for her huſbande, to meaſure his loue by it.</p>
               <q>Eſt tibi plus catus quam Papae Pontificatus.</q>
               <p>She may beare no partaker of her huſbands honeſt loue, where ſhe ruleth as Quéene. She is to be counted very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable if ſhe procure them no hatred, or vouchſafe it not her ſelfe. Theſe Stepmothers be againſt their wils great teachers of Philoſophy, but their lucke is ill in making ſew good Philoſophers. The cauſe is, for that they (for the moſt part) wiſh and would that all their huſbandes children were rather fooles than wittie, or well deſeruing: ſo well it would make for their part and purpoſe. And becauſe they be themſelues parties of ſo good meriſe, one <hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> mentioneth in an Epigram, that a young fellow whoſe Stepdame was lately deceaſed, would haue pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ouer her Toome or Hearſe (I wot not of what mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning intent) a freſh and faire garlande: it happended ſo that by moouing or medling with the Hearſe or Toome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, it fell on his legges, and did him ſuch hurt that hée neuer recouered it after. By which example, Stepdames are to bee feared and taken héede of, euen when they bée dead. What ſhoulde I ſaye? there is in Stepdames ſo much wylineſſe and boldneſſe to attempt euen the vtter moſt mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es of exterminating and vndooing of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandes children, that in all ages and degrées there haue béene ſonne in lawes brought to ruine and deſtruction by them. I wot not whether I ſhould impute it more to the huſbands effeminateneſſe and follie, than to the womans wylie woorking and dexteritie. Iuno though a goddeſſe counted afterwardes, bearing the like loue to her huſbands ſome Hercules, whiles he was yet but in his cradle, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to ſhift into him two venemous adders, in ſtéed of two pretie birds, for the litle boy to play with: but by the mercy and prouidence of God, who defendeth innocentes which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22657:19"/>are <hi>ſine macula ante thronum Dei,</hi> the poore childe was ſounde ſafe without hurt, clipping faſt the two ſnakes in ech hand one.</p>
               <p>But this was not all ſhe ſkath and ſorrow ſhe wrought him, for beſides this, when he came to mans ſtate and perfection, thoſe monſtrous toyles which were called Hercules labours, were deuiſed by her, and enioyned to him to performe and accompliſh. The Britaine King <hi>Vortimer</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Vortiger,</hi> was poyſoned by <hi>Rawen</hi> his Stepdame.</p>
               <p>The Saxon King, Edward the ſonne of <hi>Edgar,</hi> was killed on his horſebacke by procurement of <hi>Elphreda</hi> his deceaſed Fathers wife, becauſe ſhe would haue her ſonne <hi>Etheldred</hi> King. But might there be no more examples brought foorth of the like bad dealinges in former ages, then ſuch as are onely regiſtred of Kinges? Or be there not in our preſent age many meaner miſchieuous dealings of as bad teſtimonie for this purpoſe? No doubt yes: but this is enough to enforce any indifferent man to be of this opinion: that as an euill man may bee compared with manie woemen that be counted good, ſo doth a Step<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame little differ from the iuſt proportion of an euill woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. And often times the hatred both of the one and the other, is borne againſt them that be good euen for truth or goodneſſe ſake.</p>
               <p>Truely enough it may bée ſayde after the ſentence of ſome wiſe men, <hi>There is no euill more greeuous than a Step-mother.</hi> It was therefore ordayned as a lawe by <hi>Charondas</hi> a lawe giuer among the Grecians, that <hi>Whoſoeuer brought vnto his children a Stepmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſame father ſhould be without the fauour and reputation of bearing anie office in the common wealth.</hi> Neyther was his iudgement or opinion héerein to be thought ſingular or priuate, which was receiueb as an inuiolable lawe to a wiſe Nation. And of the like minde was <hi>Euripides</hi> the Philoſopher a man counted of no leſſe wiſedome and fame, when hee ſayde: <hi>Qui
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22657:19"/>liberis ſuis Nouercam ſuperinduxit, non honore dignus, ſed infamis ſit, vipote diſſentionis author</hi> that is to ſay, who ſo bringeth a Stepdame vppon his children, lette him not bee worthy of worſhip or reputation, but rather counted infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</p>
               <p>Phineus King of Arcadia, bringing a Stepdame vnto his children, ſhée wrought ſo, that in ſhorte ſpace ſhée pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the eyes of ſome of them to bée put out. For the which acte God was diſpleaſed wyth him, and depriued the King of his owne ſight, and for a worſe puniſhment, when ſoeuer he ſhoulde go to his meate, there did vſually come certaine cruell birdes or ſpirites like Harepies, to ſcratch the meate out of his handes and mouth, whereby hée was ſo vexed and pined in his diet, that hée liued not long tyme after.</p>
               <p>The worde Stepdame is not of vnkinde calling, but of harde and iniurious dealing. For we can not truely call her a mother, who ſheweth her ſelfe rather a perſecuter then a Nurſe and comforter. It is a ſaying, or reſolute Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of hym that yée call Maiſter of the Sentences, <hi>Non ſunt filij ſanctorum qui loca tenent ſanctorum, ſed qui imitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur opera ſanctorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe be not the ſomes of holy men or ſucceſſors of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Biſhops that occupie their Seates and places, but ſuch as followe their ſteppes and doings. Likewiſe we may ſay theſe be not mothers, becauſe they be coupled with fathers, but ſuch are to be called mothers, as ſuccéede them in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly dealing and kindeneſſe. But that is not agréeable vnto the nature and propertie of a ſtepmother: who for the moſt part is enclined rather vnder the ſhape and milde looks of a Doue, to beare at length the ſtinging tayle of a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion.</p>
               <p>Then what is the remedie? Euen as there be manie euilles done or borne with vnder the name of Iuſtice, ſo I wote not howe we may reſiſt or auoide theſe ſundrie incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences hatched and ſhrowded vnder the name and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnitie of marriage. But this is to be wiſhed, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22657:20"/>in ſuch caſe ſhoulde ſomewhat ſtriue to maiſter their owne fleſhly affections, that they doe auoide ſuch miſchiefs as he ouer déere bought, Eccleſiaſt ſaieth, A wiſe man hath his eyes in his head, and not in the ground, nor below the girdle, that is to ſay, he hath regarde to ſoule health, and concorde of his houſe, and other ghoſtly good of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie if he will. Which otherwiſe doth redounde the more vnto his blame and ſinnefull defaulte. It is a ſaying of Saint Gregorie: <hi>Non poteſt eſſe pastoris excuſatio, ſi lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus oues commedit &amp; paſtor neſcit.</hi> It can not bée a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient excuſe for a Paſtour or Gouernour, when his flocke is deuoured by the Woolfe to ſaie hée knewe not of it. And when children are infected wyth grudging mallice, diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and diſobedience, brought quite out of kindelie loue and fauour: and depriued of ſuch comforte and benefite as otherwiſe might come vnto them, it is not a full excuſe for the father to ſaie: It was her dooing, and not mine. I founde beſt eaſe or contentment, by ſuffering her for to beare the ſway, and for to haue her owne will. Or thus. It was my fortune, and who may reſiſte the ordinance of GOD? Forſooth a goodlie excuſe, by a gay gloſe, when hée doth blame GOD for his owne fancie and follie, and imputeth the faulte of his farewell to Fortune, which wrought no more in his matter then the Croſſe in Cheape ſide, or the Paſquill at Rome. Well dooth hée deſerue the reprehenſion of Chaweer in this péece of méeter following:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>He that buildeth his houſe all of Sallowes,</l>
                  <l>And pricketh his blinde horſe ouer the fallowes,</l>
                  <l>And ſuffreth his wife to goe ſeeke hallowes.</l>
                  <l>Is worthy &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But this ſaying ſéemes too light for the greatnes of ſome anens expectation. Let them take this of more waight and grauitie out of S. Mat. <hi>18. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ae homini illi per quem ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum venit, expedit ei vt ſuſpendatur mola a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aria in collo eius,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22657:20"/>&amp; de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iergatur in profundum maris.</hi> Woe bee vnto that man by whome offences come, it were better that a milſtone be hanged about his necke, and he drowned in the bottome of the Sea.</hi> Laſtly, to conclude on this pointe briefly with theſe few wordes, from whence come theſe euill fruites and effectes of a Stepdame, but from the will and affection of him that might haue auoided them, or els had it in his power to reſiſt, expell, or moderate them?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. That Stepdames ought not to bee priuy or falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of their huſbands children.</head>
               <p>THe moſt nimble and cunning dice plaiers, are not wont altogether to truſt to their lucky caſting and good chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the dice, whereby to make the beſt game of the ſkill, but do finde it often a principall helpe and furtherannce if they can carrie the gayne and game away with lying, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and periury. As woemen by nature are all counted weake: ſo ſome of them are borne malicious beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: eſpecially if they come in place where they may effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually vtter it: Hereof it commeth that ſtepdames pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile much in bringing their iniurious purpoſe to paſſe, by forging faultes in their huſbandes children. by launching out lyes and by facing out of forgery. As backebiting, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and flattering, are alwayes founde ſworne compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons together, ſo gay gloſing, ſupplanting of fauour, and falſe accuſing, are ſeldome ſeperate from ſtepdames, that can wring out hereof much commodity at their fingers ends.</p>
               <p>They that trauaile woodes and deſertes haue néede to looke to themſelues and beware of ſurpriſing of lions, bears, and tygres: But at home in Citties and priuate countrey houſes, ſome folke haue as much neede to take héede of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy ſlanderous reports, falſe accuſers and vnderminers, they that bée of this practiſe haue not yet learned or well borne away this morall and diuine precept, <hi>Quod tibi non
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22657:21"/>vis fieri alteri ne feceris.</hi> That which wouldeſt not haue done to thee, doe not to another, we ought to meaſure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens profite or hurte, force or infirmity, faultes or well deſeruings by our owne. The Canoniſt ſayeth, <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis eſt omnis illalatio falſi teſt imonij quae fit animo notabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter iniuſte no cendi ia bonis ſpiritualibus aut temporalibus,</hi> (that is) <hi>All bearing of falſe witneſſe, is ſinne vnto death, if it bee done of a minde much to hurt another wrongfully in his temporall goods or ſpiritually.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is the purpoſe or intent of a Stepdame, when by forging falſe accuſations and wrong interpretation or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of wordes priuily: ſhée bringeth thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>dren to bée abiected and caſt off, that haue not deſerued i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> but onely becauſe as a Stepdame ſhée woulde ſteppe betweene and defraude them of ſuch goods or benefites as her greedy appetite will not ſuffer her to forgoe? is it deadly ſinne? Let it bee ſo: ſhée careth little for that, ſo ſhee may haue her will and ſatiſfie her couetouſneſſe and luſty deſire.</p>
               <p>But it is tearmed deadly, becauſe it ſlaieth the Soule, yea, but ſhée is ſo wiſe and well armed, that ſhée dreadeth not, and of ſo harde a conſcience that ſhée féeleth no ſuch wounde. I ſuppoſe her armed in this action and property, becauſe Salomon ſayeth, <hi>Who ſo beareth falſe witneſſe againſt his neighbour hee or ſhee, is a verie ſpeare a ſworde or a ſharp arrowe.</hi> What is meant hereby, other then that the déedes of ſuch bée pearcing and perillous, but that he falleth vnto them which chaunceth many times to the fooliſhe and vnaduiſed, that hurt them ſelues with the ſame adge toole, wherewith they ſtrike or pricke at others. The twentie ſixe Chapter of the Prouerbes noteth the maner and vſage of the like folke, reſembling or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to ſome <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irago</hi> or miſchieuous manſlear, <hi>that ſhooteth deadly or poiſoned arrowes and dartes out of a priuy place: for ſo dealeth a diſſembler or priuy biter with his neighbour.</hi> If you wil know how accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and well pleaſing vnto God theſe make-bates and falſe accuſers be, whether they bée Stepmothers, ſuborned prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticers,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22657:21"/>malignant contriuers, or others, you may beléeue the ſixt of the Prouerbes in theſe wordes: <hi>A diſſembling tongue, a falſe witnes that bringeth vp lies and ſuch a one as ſoweth d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cord among brethren, theſe be ſuch as the Lorde hateth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although God of his mercy, or further reſpect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, doth forbeare and deferre the puniſhment of many iniquities, which are reſerued to himſelfe and not ſeuerely executed by any Iuſtice in this worlde, yet ſometimes it pleaſeth him for mans warning and inſtruction, to giue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of his diuine pleaſure for ſuch offences that be wicked and vniuſt. I meane falſe accuſing and wrong ſurmiſing, you may reade the reports of ſundrie writers, that doe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a wonderfull worke of God wrought vpon a woman of nobility, for a like offence committed rather but of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and rawnes, then of purpoſed mallice to hurt any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therewith. And becauſe particular mens wordes be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times diſtruſted, I will direct you to a ſenſible teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, whereof a multitude no doubt till this day are aliue to be eie witneſſes. At the Monaſtery of Loſdune beſides Delphe in Holland, is the Toome of the Lady Margeret Courteſſe, ſo miraculous to be remembred, whereuppon is, or of late yeares was an Epitaph written or engrauen thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here lieth Margeret the daughter of Florentius Earl of Holland, &amp; of Maudeline his wife, who was the daughter of Henry duke of Brabant, which Margeret beign of the age of forty two years An. 1276. on good Friday at nine of the clocke died, being in trauaile brought forth confuſed or myngled male and female, one with another 364. children at one birth together, which as ſoone as they had all receiued baptiſme of the Biſhop, in the preſence of a great company of ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and head officers of the countrey, al the males being called by the name of Iohn, &amp; the females Ioan, they euery one of them with their mother departed this life, their So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e eternall with God, whoſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22657:22"/>bodies lie buried here vnder this marble ſtone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The occaſion whereuppon it pleaſed God to ſhewe his miraculous power vpon this Lady in this manner is with the reſt reported to bée, for that within certaine monethes before, a poore woman bearing in her armes two children of one burden, and begging her deuotion, ſhee did diſdaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defame or rather falſly accuſe her of miſliuing: ſaying that it was not poſſible or likely, that ſhe ſhoulde haue two children lawfully at one birth, whereuppon it is ſaide, the poore woman praid God that the Lady might haue as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny children at a burden as there bee daies in the yeare. Which accident did not much faile to verifie the diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vttered in the ninth of the Prouerbs. <hi>The innocent dealing of the iuſt, ſhal lead or deliuer them, but the vnfaithfulnes of the deſpiſers ſhalbe their ende or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The truth of the matter ſeemeth as open and euident as a werte in a mans face. The perſons be named, the place is noted, and none of theſe obſcure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. That Stepmothers ought not to ſupplant or procure diſheriting of their huſbands eldeſt Sonnes.</head>
               <p>DIoniſius king of Cicill, when he ſaw his mother who was well ſtept in yéeres, to haue gotten hir an other huſband, and therby to bring her ſobriety and former chaſt behauiour in queſtion, gaue forth this ſentence vppon that action of her liking, ſaying: <hi>Truely my friends wee may violate and break the lawes of our countrey and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps eſcape vnpuniſhed, but my mother would break the law of nature and that is either impoſſible or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenient for her to doe.</hi> But king Dioniſius was not in the caſe to complaine of thoſe euils and inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are wont to ſuccéede of ſecond mariages, he ſtood not at his mother deuotion, neither might it much preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice him by her mariage: onely he ſéemed to blame her for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22657:22"/>attempting to break the law of nature, which is the firmeſt law, by abandoning hir ſelfe to the fleſh at thoſe yéeres, and by entring into a purpoſe that is wont to alienate naturall loue, and to alter motherly affection: changing them both perhaps for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traries. And to ſay the troth, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part children haue not ſo much cauſe to diſlike with their owne mothers ſecond marying, as with their fathers: ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the diceaſe of the Father they haue that which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, or they might looke for: but not ſo when the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther departeth firſt. For in that caſe there is a new worlde towards, and a turning of al vpſice downe, if the Father be not conſtant in obſeruing the law of nature, and prouident in auoiding ſuch euils and hinderances, as by another mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying are like to enſue to his preſent children, <hi>Mulieris e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatio totam turbat domum,</hi> ſaith Plautus, the couetous and contentious endeuour of a Stepmother, will make all his children ſing woe and weale away, ſhe purpoſeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow her time and night worke ſo well, that ſhe will raiſe vppe new plants and fruite that ſhall ſoone be ripe, but in the meane time ſhe wilbe ſo bolde, as to crop the others and to kéepe them as much as ſhe can from any good increaſe, &amp; ouer this at length perhaps vtterly to ſupplant and plucke them vp quite by the rootes. But ſoft you dame ſtay the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lde a while, and let mée looke if all be well for your ſurer ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. I wot a womans wiſedom is for the moſt in her wil, and her conſcience in her cubbord. I may graunt your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and honeſty to be much, but Eccleſiaſticus ſaieth: <hi>ther is no wickednes to the wickednes of a woman.</hi> Are you maried? I aſke you becauſe wée finde ſome mariages godly and ſome no more then honeſt, ſome to bee wicked, and ſome ſcarcely good, ſome well approued, and ſome no more then tollerable, ſome bee Bigamy by marrying one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and ſome marie twiſe for one wife, but all men moſt confeſſe it is a badde matrimony, that is not better then whoredome or fornication. Can you loue your huſbande and hate his children? Can you honor him or vow to ſeeke his honeſty by vndoing them? Doe you perform the vow
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22657:23"/>of your obedience, when by all meanes you can, you make him to obay and followe your iniurious will? Are you a Chriſtian by profeſſion, and yet in workes will ſhew your ſelfe worſe then a Turke of Thrace or Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, that will not perſecute Chriſtian infants, but nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and bring them vp? are you receiued to be endewed by the law, and yet will wraſtle to abuance your part with the ſpoile and impoueriſhing of them whom rather you are bound by honeſty to defend? To get as much as you can to your ſhare by flattery and iniury: this you ſay is your conſcience, and this is your counſell: truly it is but a ſory counſell, and ſecond conſcience meete for a ſecond mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. For there is another marriage to be preſerred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yours: and yet I acknowledge yours to bee lawfull and tollerable. And that is the firſt marriage of the two ſingle perſons, by the which is figured the vnion of Chriſt with the Church his ſpouſe, and therewithall ſignified the deuine loue, comfort, and faithfulneſſe towards the ſame. Which Church our Sauiour did ſanctify and clenſe by his holy Sacraments in ſuch wiſe as hee might haue it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpotte or wrinkle. And if ſo pure and immaculate a thing be figured or ſignified by the firſt marriage, it muſt follow that the ſame marriage is without ſpotte or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, which is more then the ſecond may well bee aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, as may appeare by theſe reaſons, likelihoodes and allegations following.</p>
               <p>To the firſt marriage did appertaine that Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bleſſing which in a great part of Chriſtiandome is vſed till this day, the ſame alwaies being denyed to the ſecond or third marriage. And here I conſtantly beſeech as many as would be counted profeſſors or fauorers of truth, abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſuppreſſe or deny it, that they will beare with me in ſetting downe theſe few places of teſtimony, being true: from whence ſoeuer they come.</p>
               <p>It is well knowne that for the moſt part both in the Latin &amp; Greeke church, til this day in moſt places they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not the holines of Eccleſiaſtical function any that hath
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22657:23"/>marryed twice, wherby he is called <hi>Bigamus,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reiected.</p>
               <p>By the Councell of Neoceſaria Can. <hi>3.</hi> it was conſulted vpon and decréed concerning thoſe men who marry ſundrie times, and likewiſe of the women that marry ſundry times. <hi>tempus quidem penitentiae his conſtitutum manifeſtum eſt ſed conuerſatio &amp; fides eorum tempus abbreuiat.</hi> Alſo by the ſame Councell Can. <hi>7.</hi> it was decréede, concluded, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed for an vniuerſall law, That a prieſt ought not to bée preſent at the feaſt or bridale of the ſecond or third marriage, ſpecially ſéeing he is commanded to enioyne repentance to the ſecond marriage. <hi>Quis ergo erit presbyter qui propter conuiuium illis conſentiat nuptijs,</hi> that is, what prieſt then will for the feaſt or dinners ſake ſéeme to conſent vnto that marriage? Saith the reſt of the Canon: Well, we wil ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this to be true, and that there is, or hath bin ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſſe vſed, but percaſe not meant altogether, in deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or diſabling of the ſecond marriage, but rather to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the firſt, and to aduance the dignitie of eccleſiaſticall orders. S. Hierome in an epiſtle written to a Lady or gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman, whoſe name was Ageruthia hath theſe words. <hi>Cum in ſemente terrae bonae centeſimum &amp; ſexageſimum &amp; triceſimum fructum Euangelia doceant, &amp; centenarius pro virginitatis corana, primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gradum teneat ſexagenarius pro labore viduarum, in ſecundo ſit numero, tricenarius federa nuptiarum, ipſa digitorum coniunctione teſtetur Digamia in quo erit numero, imo extra numerum, certè in bona terra non oritur, ſed in vepribus &amp; ſpinetis vulpium, quae Herodiae impijſſmae comparantur, vt in eo ſe putet eſſe laudabilem ſi ſcortis melior ſit: ſi publicanorum victimas ſuperet ſi vni ſit prostituta non pluribus:</hi> that is, Whereas the Goſpell tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth or mentioneth of a hundred folde fruit, ſixtie folde, and thirtie folde to come of the ſéede ſowne in good ground, and that the hundred folde helde the firſt and chiefe degrée for the crowne of virginitie, the ſixtie folde the ſecond degrée for the labour and good worke of widowes, the thirtie folde ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a rewarde for the true obſeruing of matrimony made
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22657:24"/>by ioyning hands. The ſtate of Digamie or ſuch as mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry twiſe, in what degrée or number be they? In déede they are in none, ſéeing it groweth not in good grounde, but in buſhes and thornes, which are compared to the wicked Herodias, that might thinke her ſelfe laudable in this point, if ſhe be ſomwhat better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that be naught, if ſhe ſerue one mans turne, &amp; not many. Diuers &amp; ſundry other proofs, reaſons, &amp; likelihoodes might be brought, that woulde ſhake and quaſle the very foundation of a Stepdames ouer great reckoning and preſumption, but this ſhall ſuffice for this turne. That which may be gathered of the aboue mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned places of teſtimony, if it be well conſidered and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ballance of a mans chriſten conſcience, I doubt not, but that any father, ſtanding in this caſe (of ſuch as haue flexible hearts, and be not ouermuch hardened) will at the length haue both an outward and inward reſpect vnto the qualitie, dignitie, and preeminence of the firſt marriage, and likewiſe the iſſue thereof: yea, and whatſoeuer he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a while, there is ſuch a remorce to be had herein, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aly if he haue iniured the firſt, as wil make his pulſes work, and his heart to drop teares, if that be enough. Which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce and remembrance of himſelf may be drawne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued, euen from example and experience in our firſt fathers the patriarchs and faithfull ſeruants of God.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of Wurmace, Doctor Bourchard, in his common places of the decrées, and counſelles Eccleſiaſtike, alleadgeth this, as the wordes of Saint Hierome: <hi>Ebron dicitur eſſe ciuitas trium virorum &amp;c.</hi> Ebron is ſaide to be the Cittie of the thrée men, becauſe in the ſame were buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the thrée Patriarchs there, in a double caue, with theyr thrée wiues: to wit, Abraham and Sara, Iſaac and Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Iacob and Lea. They had other wiues, of whome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares not the like regard: but theſe were the firſt, to whoſe ofſpring the bleſſing was due, and by whoſe fruitefulnes the heretage of the faithful, and the faith it ſelfe was maintened and vpholden by propagation and ſpreading vnto the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie from whom we clayme.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:22657:24"/>
Anſwerable to this Tobias ſaid to his ſon, <hi>Cum accepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit deus animam meam &amp;c.</hi> When GOD ſhall receiue my ſoule, thou ſhalt bury my body, and honour thy mother al the dayes of thy life: and when ſhe hath likewiſe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed her time, thou ſhalt bury her harde by me in one ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre. Saint Auguſtine hereuppon hath theſe wordes: <hi>In primo connubio coniuncti quia vna &amp; eadem caro eſt, in vno ſepulohro ſepeliantur.</hi> They that in the firſt marriage be ioined togither, foraſmuch as they be one and the ſame fleſh, it is méet they be buried in one graue or ſepulchre. If the examples of the patriarks &amp; the counſel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy doctors do perſuade and induce to bring the deceaſed fathers to their firſt ſpouſes, or the firſt eſpouſed to them in burialles, what ſhould we gather hereof, but perfection, validitie, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine allowing of the one: weakeneſſe, clement tolleration, and ſcantie commending of the other.</p>
               <p>With what conſcience then may the woman of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond marriage iniure the firſt, by a ſupplanting drift and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donour of hir part? firſt rooting out all kindely good will that ſhould come towards the ſon from his father, and at length ſtripping him of the bleſſing, birthright, and heretage due by the right of laws, nature, and ſo great antiquitie. Woulde ſhe ſhrowde hir wicked working and wrong doing vnder the example of Rebecca defrauding Eſau of the bleſſing due vnto the eldeſt ſonne? No, ſhe can not, for that the caſes bée not like. Rebecca was the firſt wife, and Eſaus own mother: and alſo it came of the will and prouidence of God ſince reuealed, who knewe before what was néedefull to be done for the helpe of his Church, the planting of his faith and the encreaſe of his glorie. But as for the vſuall ſorte of Stepdames, I wote with what Spirite they be endo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed and directed, who can not ſo well chalenge to them the worthines, myſticall vnion, and right of the firſt marriage, though they be called wiues. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſhe a wrong doer by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>: vniuerſal law of cities &amp; matrons, which ſaith: <hi>locupletari no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; debet aliquis cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alterius iniuria vel iactura:</hi> no man nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought inrich the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or loſſe of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:22657:25"/>
But the diuine lawe, whoſe ſentence is moſt to be drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, gyueth a harde conſtruction, and a more ſcuere iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt any Stepdame and hir complices in the lyke wrongfull action, as appeareth in Eccleſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.34.</hi> Who ſo depriueth his neighbour of his liuing, dooth as great ſinne as though hée ſlewe hym to death. I trowe ſhe will not deny hir huſbands ſonne to be hir neighbour very neare in this meaning. Wherefore, not to be ouer tedious in this point, as ye haue heard before, the ſentence of the heauenlie King againſt the iniurious woman, deliuered by the trump of the holy Ghoſt, euen ſo let the iudgement of the earthlie Emperour Marcus Aurelius againſt the miſaduiſed father be digeſted as a pleaſant reprehenſion, and profitable admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, which is thus. He is a foole that taketh counſel of a woman, he more foole that aſketh it, but he moſt foole that fulfilleth it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. That diſheriting of the eldeſt ſonne is an acte verie wrongfull and vngodly.</head>
               <p>ONe of the Romane Emperours, though nameleſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was vicious, yet did he ordaine ſundry lawes that imported great iuſtice and humanitie: namely, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the reſt this one, That no Romane whatſoeuer ſhould caſt out of his doores, any ſeruant, ſlaue, horſe, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaſt, were it but a dogge, for olde age, ſickeneſſe, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny infirmitie, grounding and confirming his law with this reaſon: that men ſerue from their youth, to be ſuccoured when they come to olde age. Humanitie and Iuſtice are ſo vniuerſally commendable, and ſo particularly néedfull in the life of man, that we may draw infinite examples of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing &amp; due regard therof, euen from Paynims &amp; infidels, which is the loſſe to be maruelled at by this ſaying of Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo: <hi>Moriales maxime Deos imitantur quoniam bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici ſunt.</hi> All people doe followe the propertie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of GOD, becauſe he is full of good dooing. Wherof comes the prouerb, <hi>Homo homini deus:</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a god to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:22657:25"/>Yea iuſtice is ſo naturall &amp; erpedient in humaine dealings, that it is obſerued and religiouſly regarded euen towardes enemies, and not without good cauſe, ſith as Saint Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ſayth, <hi>Iuſtitia eſt radix vitae: <hi>Rightfull dealing is the roote of mans life.</hi>
                  </hi> Which as it deſerueth commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and is of all mankinde to be embraced, ſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie thereof, which is iniury and wrong-doing is no leſſe to be eſchewed. For according to the ſaying of <hi>S. Auguſt. lib. 2. Ciu. Dei Nihil homini tam inimicum quam iniuſtitia. <hi>There is nothing ſo much an enemie to man, as is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice and dooing of wrong.</hi>
                  </hi> Then is it verie vnméete that one man ſhould vſe it towardes an other. But howe much more inconuenient for a Parent, to ſhewe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for ne towardes his owne ſonne. But perchaunce you will ſay, that a Father hath eyther ſuch authoritie ouer his ſon, or ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h intereſt in that which he poſſeſſeth, and is counted his owne, that in ſuch behalfe hee cannot doe his ſonne wrong, which is to be préeued to the contrarie: and the wrong to be ſo much the greater as there is betwéene them proximi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie and néereneſſe of friendſhip, conſtitute and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the lawe of nature. And therefore as that law decréeeth i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all ſortes of thinges that the firſt ſowen ſhould be firſt ripe, and the firſt ſet, firſt to flouriſh or waxe gréene, ſo the law of reaſon willeth, that he that firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſhould be firſt ſped, ſéeing by nature he is enioyned firſt to depart. And as nature in all her workes for the moſt part ſéemeth to make ſome one thing to be chiefe before all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſame is, and the rather continueth, ſo reaſon in the order of a family, which is an imitation of a ſtate ciuile, or bodie polliticke, perſwadeth of experience &amp; neceſſitie, that there be one before the reſt as chiefe. Whereby may bée conſerued that beautie of Vnitie, and harmony of concord, which the almightie in his creation ſo woonderfully and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſely teacheth, and our Saniour him ſelfe ſo carefully and ſpecially commended to his flocke: and hereof ſéemeth to come that preeminence or more ſpeciall regard, which the lawe of God in the olde teſtament appointed to his people
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22657:26"/>the Iſraelites, to be obſerued towardes the firſt begotten ſonne, and likewiſe ſomwhat concerning other dinnbe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which firſt were brought foorth into the world.</p>
               <p>By the auncient lawe of the Iewes, the eldeſt had dubble ſo much as the others of the Fathers goods, and alone to the eldeſt pertayned the bleſſing of the Father wherewith ſhould ſéeme alwayes the heritage to goe and ſuccéede: as appeareth by the will of God in Deut. <hi>21. Thou ſhalt not make the ſonne of the ſeconde wife heire, before him that is firſt borne, though his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were hated. For to him belongeth the right of the firſt borne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Patriarkes and others the ſeruantes of God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by diuine reuelation and other notice of the will of God they were certified that they might marry many or ſundry wiues at one time, yet did they exclude from their heritage and prerogatiue of the bleſſing, all the children of thoſe ſecondarie and after marriages, this appeareth by Gen. <hi>21. The Sonne of the bonde woman ſhall not be heire with my ſonne Iſaac.</hi> Yet he was the eldeſt, but was not the ſonne of the firſt marriage. Alſo an heire is the worke and inſtitution of nature, and heritage is dew to the ſonne by nature, therefore it is ſo dewe that hee muſt néedes haue it: ſéeing thoſe thinges which come by nature or be naturall are not mutable, or to be chaunged. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this name heire, which in a manner with all Nations is the eldeſt, hee is the ſucceſſor of the lawe Nationall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the lawes naturall and diuire. And that Father who maketh an other heire than is by theſe authorities appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, can not but expreſſe himſelfe rebell in diſobeying &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenming ſo great lawes and authoritie beginning a newe lawe of his owns head contrarie thereunto.</p>
               <p>Then what is more vniuſt, than to doe contrarie to all lawes, and therewith to diſobey the will of God, to peruert the dew order of diſcent, preferring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond mariage before the firſt, diſprayſed Bigamy before the mariage beſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; honored with the merite of the thirtiefold frute, as S.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22657:26"/>Hierome ſayth: The younger before the elder, the later of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fpring before <hi>primogenitum,</hi> ſo much tendered and reſpected?</p>
               <p>Now as the greateſt iniury a Father can do to his ſonne is to diſherite him, ſo is it the moſt reprochfull blot or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to ſuffer the infamy &amp; diſcredite of diſheriſon. For if he be worthy to be diſherited in his fathers houſe, hee may be thought not woorthy to drawe breath out of it: for that he ought to be conuinced faulty in thoſe crimes &amp; hainous offences which be either repugnant to the dutie of a child, or not méete for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profeſſion of a chriſtian. Namely if he ſtrike or offer violence to his Father. If he oppreſſeth him with ſome great wrong. If he ſéeke his death or deſtruction by poyſoning or otherwiſe. If he lye with his fathers wife. If he will not ſuffer his father to make his will. If he be not of the true and Catholike ſayth, but is conuinced to be an Hereticke, whereby his life and heritage is in hazard. Or if he refuſe to ſuccour and deliuer his father out of priſon by his ſuertiſhip, or if hee followe the trade and company of ſuch perſons as in the lawe be counted <hi>infames,</hi> as wée ſay infamous, vile, and moſt diſhoneſt, as Iuglers, Sorcerers, Coniurers, Théeues, and Pirates. Or if the Father offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him méete marriage vnder fine and twentie yeares, he refuſeth it, and delighteth to liue continually in whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and filthie order of life, theſe be (I ſuppoſe) all the cauſes that the Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall lawes doe aſſigne.</p>
               <p>And yet doe ſome Doctors of the Church make it a queſtion, whether a ſonne ought to be diſherited at all for any of theſe cauſes. But all doe agrée, that ſéeing diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon is of all others moſt odious, and vtterly contrarie to the office and dutie of nature a man ought not to fall to diſheriting, nor yet <hi>ad preteritionem,</hi> which is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting or putting out of the will, except it be for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt or worſt deſeruinges by theſe cauſes. In which caſe of diſheriting, there is noted this ſentence or iudgement of the holy Doctor S. Aug. <hi>Quicunque vult exheredato filio here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem facere, Doctore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſiaſticu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaerat alteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui cauſam ſuſcipiat non Auguſtinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, immo Deo propitio nemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inueniet:</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:22657:27"/>whoſo euer (ſayeth he) diſheriting his ſonne would make an other heire, let him ſéeke an other Doctor of the Church to meddle with the cauſe, and not Auguſtine: but by the grace of God he ſhall finde none. But the iudgement of whome, and of the moſt part of all other good and learned men, that vnkinde practiſe of diſheriting, ſéemeth both ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde and vngodly among the people of Chriſtes flocke: ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we are all called to claime our owne birthright, and do deſire to attaine vnto that inheritance of the kingdome of heauen which is but one.</p>
               <p>If one brother diſherite an other contrarie to the will of the father, may not the father by common equitie thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretend cauſe of diſheriting the diſheritor? We are all brothers, and the ſonnes of one heauenly father. We are all ſo fraile, and giuen to offende, that we are not fit to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite, but rather ſhould feare to be diſherited.</p>
               <p>Neither néede we to bring foorth any written examples aunſwerable in this place, ſith wee haue eye teſtimonie in manner of common experience in many: who haue diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited, vndermined, or defrauded others, and thereby haue giuen an example howe other men ſhould deale towardes them or theirs, and ſo at length haue bought with the ſame meaſure they ſolde vnto others.</p>
               <p>A learned Doctor of this age, writing vpon the matter of Teſtamentes or Willes making, hath theſe wordes worthie recitall. <hi>Prudentia &amp; bonorum virorum conſilia a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquando ſuadebunt liberos malos non omnino exheredes ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendos eſſe: ſed in eis honorandum eſſe naturam legittima portione a iure preſcripta. Illi vero parentes non digni ſunt aut parentum nomine, aut qui hac luce fruantur qui partes ſuas a ſe proijcere &amp; exponere audent. <hi>Wiſedome and the counſaile of good men</hi>
                  </hi> (ſayth he) <hi>will at one time or other perſwade that euill children are not at all to bee diſherited, but that nature be honored in them, by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them haue their lawefull portion appointed by the lawe. But thoſe Parents who caſt off their children from them are not worthy the name of Parentes nor
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22657:27"/>ſcarſe to haue the fruition of this life.</hi> If this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be ſuch according to laws eccleſiaſticall and diuine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſonnes lewdly enclined, or of ill behauiour: how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious and vniuſt doth he thinke to be the diſheriting of ſuch as be honeſtly giuen, or rather make teſtimonie of ſome vertue and valure. Yee haue heard before, that by ſomeout of Imperiall lawe aſſes and dogges were not to be caſt out of the doores, and ſhall chriſten men caſt out their owne ſons, to the reproch and ſcorning of the worlde? Aſſes may beare the waight and griefe of ſuch burdens, and dogges may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to digeſt ſuch bones: but with the moſt ſorte of men they are eyther taken as heauie at the heart as mil-ſtones, or as venomous in the intrailes as poiſon: ſome haue yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelues vnto deſparation of minde, and therevppon haue runne madde. Others haue addicted themſelues vnto damnable trades, as of robbery, piracie, coniuration, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and others, in hatred of that bad vnkinde mind of their parents, haue forſaken true Religion, and fallen into Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometiſme, or other peruerſe &amp; reprobate ſence of doctrine. Others that haue béene of more credite or power, haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into moſt bloody facts of warre and conſpiracies, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of haue enſued vncharitable broiles, and more then vnchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian contentions: all procéeding from the roote of ſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the like iniurie, or more rather from the Iuſtice of GOD, who would not leaue ſo high an example of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice and wrong dooing vnpuniſhed.</p>
               <p>And although the acte of Diſheriſon is rare and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous among good men, yet ſuch as put it in practiſe, will thinke they may the rather doe it, becauſe others haue done it before them. Vnto whome Seneca anſwereth, ſaying: There is no wickednes which a man may not finde taught by example, if he be ſo ready to followe it.</p>
               <p>Some other fathers there be, who being caried away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to partiality and wrong iudgement, by the perſwaſion of women (of whoſe partes and practiſe you haue ſufficiently heard) will pretende, and lay vnto their ſonnes charge, the accuſation of ill Religion: Let ſuch Parents take héed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22657:28"/>leaſt bearing the name of Chriſtians, they be found perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuters of the ſame. It is a more then fault to render euill for good, or to reward vertue with puniſhment. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not ſafetie for any father of meane knowledge him ſelfe to condemne his ſonne to diſheriſon in a difficult cauſe: ſo much he may be deceiued and blinded by the wrong per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of a woman, and by other fine flatterie of ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed friends.</p>
               <p>But if it would pleaſe ſuch a father as is enclined by anie manner of meanes to diſherite his ſonne, to looke vnto him ſelfe: and ſetting apart affection in matters of controuerſie, to weigh his owne euill with his owne good, no doubt hée would confeſſe and ſay with the Poet:</p>
               <q>Peccantem damnare caue, nam labimur omnes.</q>
               <q>Condemne not him that offendeth, for we al do offend</q>
               <p>He might ſée, that in his life he hath done but little good as he ſhould do. No works of vertue, none of charitie, none of true godlineſſe, little of kindeneſſe, none of chaſtitie, litle of trueth, none of true faith, but rather all to the contrary, laying aſide mercie, and refuſing to vouchſafe and performe the effectes of forgiueneſſe vnto his owne ſonne, ſo much is his vnderſtanding peruerted, and his heart hardened, which, I feare me, may boade vnto anie father little good, ſith it is the ſaying of Saint Bernard: <hi>Nemo vnquam cordis duri, bonum habuit, niſi forte commiſerans Deus abſtulit cor lapideum &amp; contulit carneum,</hi> that is, Neuer any man gotte any good by his hard heart, vnles peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture when it pleaſeth GOD of his infinite mercie to take from him his ſtonie heart, and giue vnto him a heart of fleſh.</p>
               <p>then well hée ſée his owne ouerſight, in omitting to giue good examples of naturall loue and affection to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp; therwithal perceiue what had fruits he hath reapt by his examples of vnkindees, hard dealing, and peruerting of order in his family. Then will be find what ghoſtly comfort a peaceable &amp; charitable mind haue in auoiding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dangerous flames of wrath &amp; inward diſquietnes. Then it will appéere
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22657:28"/>howe beneficiall and happie it had beene for his children, and how godly and ſéemely for him ſelfe if hee had followed ſound counſaile, and the prompting of grace in diſobeying thoſe his luſts and wilfull liking, the ſeruing and pleaſing whereof, hath heaped vpon him thoſe euils, which he finde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth now ſo hardly to be remembred. And further that gay-ſhew of a womans loue, which firſt was founded either v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the hope and opinion of his wealth, or of purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraude and depriue his firſt children of inwarde affection or outward poſſibility, now will ſéeme vading and vaniſhing like the moone before her change. Now wil tourne to his remembrance thoſe cauſes of ſorrow and griefe which were giuen to his own children, by her malignity in bringing t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of his fauour into hatred and diſpleaſure: then will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of wrong doing, ſpecially in ſupplanting and diſheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (if any be) compas him on euery ſide. On the right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſee how hée hath continued and caſt from him the due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard and worthineſſe of the firſt mariage. On the left hand how prepoſterouſly he hath delt againſt nature &amp; order pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the pleaſing of an iniurious woman before al lawes and dutifull reſpects. Behind him in calling to mind, how he hath left the pattern of an ill example for others, and a bad teſtimony of conſcience for himſelfe. Before him the orderly dealing of all wiſe, godly, &amp; prouident fathers euident to his reproofe and reproche: Beneath him the deapth of due ſorro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing and repentance, together with the ponderous w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight of his ſinnes augmented by her ſpinning. Aboue him the hope of his mercifull fauour whome he hath moſt offended, and the expectation for a heauenly inheritance for himſelfe who diſobeyd the diuine will, in more then denying to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his eartly portion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. That procurors and counſailors of diſheriſon, and all wrong doing, ought to make or procure reſtitution,</head>
               <p>That famous Duke Alcibiades comming to viſit Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles a man of equal fame, who praid him not to trouble
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22657:29"/>him at that time, becauſe he was bethinking himſelfe how to giue an account to the whole ſtate of Athens, then quoth Alciabiades, were it not rather better to deuiſe howe you may not giue an account at all. Although perchaunce Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibiades meaning was naught and corrupte herein, yet his words be true, for euerie man knoweth it is more ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſhunne and auoide the caſe of rendring accomps, then to bée charged and entangled therewith. Man that hath paſt his time in this worlde, rather according to the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite of the fleſh and direction of his malicious and iniurious, will then after the counſaile of the ſpirite and motion of grace, well and happy it were for him, if either his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency were ſuch, as a ſmall reckoning before God woulde ſerue, or his carefull regarde in making a due account and reconciliation with God, were ſo truely perfourmed here in this worlde, that he might finde the leſſe difficulty and daunger in the worde to come. But when will he perform it that differreth it from day to day, or rather from year to yeare? and when will hee goe about it, that will not begin it till his ending day, or perhaps thinketh not of it at all. How perillous a matter ſuch folke of their impiety or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence doe vouchſafe to their owne ſoule, this ſaying of Saint Auguſtine <hi>in ſer. de Jnnocen.</hi> might ſomewhat certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them. The ſinner (ſayeth he) may take this for a ſure leſſon, that at the time of his death he ſhalbe vnmindfull of him ſelfe, who when hee liued was forgetfull of God, and therefore Saint Paul to the Galathians counſalleth vs with theſe wordes: <hi>Dum tempus habemus operemur bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Whiles wée haue time let vs worke good, nay rather the moſt part, haue néede to leaue euill and fall to repentance. It is not inough to goe diligently to the Church, except the conſcience be in his due eſtate, the paiment of naughty mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doth not diſcharge a mans debt, ſith the principall thing pertaining to man or betwéene God and man is conſcience as for good workes they be but things acceſſory, if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bée wrapped in ſinne, or thereby wounded to death, what ſoeuer a man doth, wée may doubt whether it be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22657:29"/>
                  <hi>Reſpexit dominus ad Abel &amp; ad munera eius.</hi> Ge. <hi>4</hi> The Lord had reſpect to Abell and to his oblations. O good God, thou knoweſt the multitude of offences which procéed from the naughty inclination of our own body, euen of ſuch men as be counted honeſt and good men in the world. Full little néedes any to augment the huge burden of their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by outward wrong dooing, or by partaking in the like offences of others. It hath bin before ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhewed and prooued, that birthright is right: &amp; ſuch as God himſelfe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not to be wronged. We are tolde by the ghoſtly aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement of Eccl. <hi>43.</hi> Who ſo depriueth his neighbour of his liuing, doth as great ſinne as though he ſlue him to death. Then, no doubt, he that procureth or counſelleth to take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another that which is his, or els is the means whereby it is taken away, or not réſtored, he, or they, not only ſin deadly, but are alſo bound to make reſtitution. Remember what our Sauior ſaith Mat. <hi>5. <hi>Non exies inde donec reddes nouiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum quadrantem,</hi>
                  </hi> thou ſhalt not depart thence vntill thou ſhalt reſtore the laſt farthing.</p>
               <p>It is the common admonition of ſpirituall paſtors, <hi>Non dimittitur peccatum, niſi restituatur ablatum.</hi> The ſinne of wrong doing is not forgiuen, vnleſſe that be reſtored which was taken away. If he be bound in the lawe to make reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, that holds but a doue houſe to the knowen &amp; euident dammage of his neighbors in their corne: how much rather be or they that take away a whole ſhip lode by Sea, or a farm at land: but the wrong of birthright &amp; inheritance dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth more déeply then a ſhip, &amp; is of more importance to be regarded in the matter of reſtitution then a farme.</p>
               <p>S. Aug. <hi>lib. de Penitent.</hi> ſaieth thus, <hi>Ad agendam peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam non ſufficit mores melius conuertere, &amp; à malefactis resedere, niſi de his quae facta ſunt ſatisfaciat domino per pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiae dolorem.</hi> To the performing of repentance, it is not enough for a man to change his manners, or to amend his life vnles he pleaſe God by a ſufficient ſorrowing of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But it is not meant hereby, that in performing due penance or repentance it is enough for a man to be ſorie.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22657:30"/>For the ancient Doctors do teach, that repentance conſiſts of <hi>3.</hi> parts, contrition, confeſſion, and ſatiſfaction: and thoſe doctors of latter ages, who ſay it conſiſts only of <hi>2.</hi> parts, affirme the duty of reſtitution and ſatiſfaction to be one: but whether there be thrée parts or but two, you ſhall finde due repentance a hard matter to perform, if we may beléeue the holy doctor S. Ambroſe, who ſaieth thus, <hi>Plures inuem qui innocentiam ſeruauerunt quam qui veram penitentiam age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi> I haue found more that haue not hurt any man, then which haue performed due penance or repentance. Oh, but ſome of theſe wrong doers, and ill cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellors, or coadiutors, will defend their iniurious déedes by ſcripture: they may as wel defend lying, robberie, manſlaughter, fighting, and ſtrife making, expeſting, or caſting out of the poore. For of twoo contrarieties one will ſerue their turne.</p>
               <p>To maintaine lying. <hi>Abraham lyed. Gen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the holy Ghoſt <hi>ſaith in the Pſal. 5. Thou ſhalt deſtroy all them that ſpeake lyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale. Thou ſhalt ſpoile Egypt</hi> ſaith an other place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I came not to ſend peace but the ſword Mat. 10.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My peace I giue you peace I leaue to you. Ioh. 14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that hath a coate, let him ſell it and buy him a ſworde. Luke. 22.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that taketh the ſworde ſhall periſh with the ſword. Mat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There ſhall be no needy perſon nor begger among you. Deut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The poore ye ſhall haue alwaies with you,</hi> faith the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>And what wickedneſſe may they not bee comforted or nouriſhed in by theſe wordes, <hi>Nolo mortem peceatoris,</hi> I will not the death of a Sinner. <hi>Ezech. 18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that worketh iniquitie ſhall dye in the ſame. Ezech. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We thinke (ſaith <hi>S. Paule</hi>) that man is <hi>iuſtifyed by ſaith without the workes of the law. Rom. 3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:22657:30"/>
But the ſame ſpirite ſaith, <hi>God ſhall rewarde euery man according to his doings. Rom. 2.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But true it is that in the like doubtfulneſſe or ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we ought to followe this rule, <hi>Non intentio verbis, ſed verba deſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ire debent intentioni,</hi> that is, We muſt not weſt a mans meaning to the words, but the words ſhould he brought to agrée with the ſenſe or meaning. To returne againe to the matter of timely reſtitution, and of deferring the ſame, S. Aug. hath theſe wordes: <hi>Non inueni in quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que millibus annis ſaluatum in fine ſuo niſi ſolum latronem. <hi>I find not any where of any that was ſaued at the very ending of his life, but only the theeſe.</hi>
                  </hi> Alſo ſome diuine ſayth: they who deferre to performe the parts of repentance vntill extreme infirmitie come, be in the caſe of law <hi>De ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us cedendis:</hi> where it is adiudged that the trée ſhall be his, in whoſe ground it grew and was rooted: and not to be his in whoſe ground it fell. So it is to be thought of l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n who ſo long as he liued, ſtoode by his unpenitencie in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>els ſoyle, &amp; at his death fell towardes God into the ground of his ſaluation by ouer late repentance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And many there be that can like well enough of the beginning of repentance which is dew ſorrowing of heart, and could vouchſafe to procéede vnto confeſſion by mouth, but they can not away with this reſtitution, leaſt it ſhould vtterly begger them or their children, or make them to be the worſe able to liue in the world by it. But ſuch are fooliſhly cruell, or cruell fooles to their owne ſoule, who chuſt rather the ſtate of damma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than to be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed here with a little pouertie. But let all vngodly wrong dooers, and ſuch as get goods or landes by hooke and by crooke, together with their counſellors and aſſiſtents, not vtterly deſpiſe this hiſtoricall example leaſt it may happen to be verefied in themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anthonius de Florentia</hi> a Doctor of ſome confinned cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and fame, reporteth that there was a certaine vſuror, who would not make reſtitution of the money gayned by intereſt: alleaging if he ſhould ſo doe, his children might go begge, or be ſent to the Hoſpitall. The father dyeth in the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22657:31"/>ſame ſtate, his eldeſt ſonne ſuccéedeth, and likewiſe wiſt not reſtore, The younger brother demandeth h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s part of thoſe goods and reſtoreth vnto the parties after the rate of his protion: the reſt that remayneth he giueth to the poore, and entereth into the ſtate and trade of ſolitary li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Shortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the eldeſt brother dyeth, whereupon was ſhewed to the younger brother liuing in chaſt contemplation this viſion following: He ſéeth his father and his brother in torment, one curſing the other, the father ſaying that the ſonne was the cauſe of his damnation, becauſe it was for the loue and enciching of him, that he did not make reſtitution of the money gayned by vſurie or intereſt. The ſonns he curſed and ſayde, that his father was the cauſe of his danmation, becauſe he left him theſe ill gotten goods, the kéeping wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath wrought his perdition. The example is full of terror ſpecially to ſuch as haue ill gotten goods in their handes, or elſe are intangled with the iniquitie thereof, who in their life time peraduenture will not make reſtitution the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, at the like perill, nor yet at the extreame point ſende for or admit any good man of knowledge to enforme them, and conſult with, leaſt this aduiſe might be to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> worldes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſite. To be ſhort, if procure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> counſellers of diſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon and wrong dooers themſelues, are not yet by grace prepared to receiue and followe theſe wholeſome admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of diuine Doctors, yet at leaſt it were to bee wiſhed they would take the beſt of Artib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es meaning before ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, which was to deuiſe how a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ny not be charged at all for thoſe thinges, which otherwiſe he is to accompt for.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:31"/>
            <head>Ric. Par. in Nycticoracem Iohannis <hi>Newnam Carmen.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>RVſtica Nycticorax viuens vectenſibus agris,</l>
            <l>Per mare, per terras, nocte diéque volat,</l>
            <l>Vt done extremas vrbis perting it ad oras:</l>
            <l>Fortunáque meas incidit illa manus.</l>
            <l>Hanc ego perſpiciens, alitis cognoſcere mores,</l>
            <l>Quam primum rediens ad mea tecta volo.</l>
            <l>Viſa loquax nimium eſt: nec garrula vellet haberi,</l>
            <l>Súntque haec arbitrij verba relata mei,</l>
            <l>Miſſa columba Noe ramum ſemel ore reportat:</l>
            <l>Nycticorax fructus attulitore duos.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Henr. Serae gen. in eandem Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia <hi>non ſera.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>QVid ſimulas coniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? magis eſt laudata colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ba,</l>
            <l>Corue places ſatis: at grata colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ba magis.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>In Zoilum.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>CVr tumes iratus nulli niſi dira nocenti,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Omen Nycticorax Zoile triſte canit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22657:32"/>
               <l>YOu ſhew what Fathers ought and how,</l>
               <l>to vſe their goods and pelfc:</l>
               <l>You giue them rule that neuer were,</l>
               <l>a Father yet your ſelfe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You heape your ſtuffe in had aray,</l>
               <l>no Methode in your worke:</l>
               <l>Your building baſe I thinke it ſure,</l>
               <l>more cauſe to lie and lurke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You fourde vs of your chaffe and ſtraw,</l>
               <l>you kéepe your corne in ſtackes:</l>
               <l>Your labours like to that of Bées,</l>
               <l>wée féede vppon your waxe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To all you ſeeme to preach that are,</l>
               <l>no Prophet in your dw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e:</l>
               <l>A ſhallow ſoile that ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ds you not,</l>
               <l>in credit déeper growne.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>For promiſe made of ſolid proofe, Performance is but poore:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Sa. L. Ar. Auctori carmen beneuolum.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>MAgna cadunt multis, mediocria nulla cadenti,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Magna pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as Vectilectus in vrbe liber.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Munia multa mones, viuens, ſine munere ſcriptor,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Qui ſatis eſt alijs, Vtilis eſſe potest.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Dat Deus omne bonu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſed non per cornuataurum,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Det tibi pro meritis munus amice Vale.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:32"/>
            <head>Aunſweres by the Auctor.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVIth wiſe and graue a beardleſſe man,</l>
               <l>full oft ſome credite beares:</l>
               <l>Let Fathers not diſdaine to heare,</l>
               <l>a ladde with froſty heares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Faire gliſtering ſhewes be ſeldome golde,</l>
               <l>your buildings bée too fine:</l>
               <l>In rude diſperſed Abbay roomes,</l>
               <l>a man might ſuppe and dine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although there were but lefte inough,</l>
               <l>to bake your ſelfe a cake:</l>
               <l>Proue when you will to threſh as much:</l>
               <l>will make your heart to ake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A ſhallow ſhifte ſo ſhaps him friends,</l>
               <l>and ſpeedes with ſhallow doomes:</l>
               <l>That ſhallow hearts to ſhallow mindes,</l>
               <l>muſt yeeld the ſhallow roomes.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Vnlight: pas in &amp; ſhew your male: I opened you the doore.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>MAgnacadunt mulis, ſeſſoribus atque caballi,</l>
               <l>Magne peris vento vectus in Orbe labor.</l>
               <l>Dat Deus omne bonum ſed ceruis cornua tantum:</l>
               <l>Vulpinae caude ſorſque fabella mihi eſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Great fortune fals on backes of mules:</l>
               <l>ſome hackneis on their fraight.</l>
               <l>Tho ſayling toile on worlds globe,</l>
               <l>ſome times doth periſh ſtraight.</l>
               <l>God giues all good and I ſhall haue,</l>
               <l>ſith Harts no hoofes doe want:</l>
               <l>A flappe with Rainard foxe his taile,</l>
               <l>or els my lotte is ſcant.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22657:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
